<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: audiobooks | Trey Hunner]]></title>
  <link href="https://treyhunner.com/blog/categories/audiobooks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://treyhunner.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-11-24T08:36:51-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://treyhunner.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Trey Hunner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My favorite audiobooks of 2024 (and also 2017 through 2023)]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2024/12/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2024/"/>
    <updated>2024-12-31T08:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2024/12/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2024</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I listen to <em>many</em> audiobooks every year.
I wrote recaps of my favorites in <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2014/12/top-6-books-of-2014/">2014</a>, <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2015/12/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2015/">2015</a>, and <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2017/01/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2016/">2016</a> and then I stopped doing annual recaps.</p>

<p>After a 7 year hiatus, I&rsquo;m attempting to start this annual habit again, starting with audiobooks I read in 2024.
But first, I&rsquo;ll reflect on some of the books that have stuck with me from 2017 through 2023.</p>

<h2>Books that have stuck with me from 2017 to 2023</h2>

<p>Of the 206 books I read over the 7 years of 2017 through 2023, about 35 books really stuck with me and I would recommend reading all of them.</p>

<p>Each section in ordered roughly by how much I would generally recommend the book (the first book in each section I usually recommend more than the last).
I enjoyed all these books, but I didn&rsquo;t write a review for all of them.
I&rsquo;ve included links when I did write a review.</p>

<p>Really enjoyable Sci-Fi (and a bit of Fantasy) that&rsquo;s stuck with me:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4282500474">Dawn</a></strong> (and also <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4940269595">Adulthood Rites</a>) by Octavia Butler</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5206254350">The Long Way to a Small, Angry Planet</a></strong> (&amp; <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5309212833">A Closed and Common Orbit</a>) by Becky Chambers</li>
<li><strong>The Fifth Season</strong> (and the other 2 books in the series) by N.K. Jemisin</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5851342829">Hive Minds Give Good Hugs</a></strong> by Natalie Maher</li>
<li><strong>Parable of the Sower</strong> (and <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4024406874">Parable of the Talents</a>) by Octavia Butler</li>
<li><strong>A Song for a New Day</strong> by Sarah Pinsker</li>
<li><strong>The City We Became</strong> by N.K. Jemisin</li>
</ul>


<p>Books on human progress (to extinguish your cynicism):</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Enlightenment Now</strong> by Steven Pinker</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3578812646">Factfulness</a></strong> by Hans Rosling</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4173349209">The Fabric of Civilization: How Textiles Made the World</a></strong> by Virginia Postrel</li>
</ul>


<p>The book that has most shaped my charitable giving habits:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3194541050">The Life You Can Save</a></strong> by Peter Singer (<a href="https://www.thelifeyoucansave.org/booktopia/">free here</a>)</li>
</ul>


<p>My favorite self-improvement books:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3954320132">Mind Management, Not Time Management</a></strong> by David Kadavy</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3904322364">The Scout Mindset</a></strong> by Julia Galef</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2739759842">Deep Work</a></strong> by Cal Newport</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3103304459">The Joy of Movement</a></strong> by Kelly McGonigal</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5863937406">Learn Like a Pro</a></strong> by Barbara Oakley, Olav Schewe</li>
<li><strong>Atomic Habits</strong> by James Clear</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3175104288">Good Habits, Bad Habits</a></strong> by Wendy Wood</li>
</ul>


<p>Books on economics, government, and public policy that aren&rsquo;t about housing and city planning:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4698620684">Basic Economics: A Citizen&rsquo;s Guide to the Economy</a></strong> by Thomas Sowell</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5665700932">Recoding America</a></strong> by Jennifer Pahlka</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4022258349">Drug Use for Grown-Ups: Chasing Liberty in the Land of Fear</a></strong> by Carl L. Hart</li>
<li><strong>How Rights Went Wrong</strong> by Jamal Greene</li>
</ul>


<p>Books on housing and city planning that have shaped my YIMBY-ish views:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4296215248">Happy City</a></strong> by Charles Montgomery</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5559905236">Arbitrary Lines: How Zoning Broke the American City and How to</a></strong> by M. Nolan Gray</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4296213335">Walkable City: How Downtown Can Save America, One Step at a Time</a></strong> by Jeff Speck</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5716387928">Paved Paradise: How Parking Explains the World</a></strong> by Henry Grabar</li>
</ul>


<p>Books on xenophobia and other-ing that have particularly stuck with me:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Caste</strong> by Isabel Wilkerson</li>
<li><strong>The Sum of Us: What Racism Costs Everyone and How We Can Prosper Together</strong> by Heather McGhee</li>
</ul>


<p>Books that have impacted my <em>very gradual</em> journey toward veganism:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/5908347928">Why We Love Dogs, Eat Pigs, and Wear Cows</a></strong> by Melanie Joy</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3597337038">The End of Animal Farming</a></strong> by Jacy Reese Anthis</li>
</ul>


<p>TV shows I&rsquo;ve (so far) liked more than the books they&rsquo;re based on:</p>

<ul>
<li>Silo (Apple TV)</li>
<li>The Power (Amazon Prime)</li>
<li>The Three-Body Problem (Netflix, though Amazon Prime has a much slower Chinese version)</li>
</ul>


<p>Note that the above books do not include books I listened to in 2014, 2015, and 2016.
See <a href="https://treyhunner.com/blog/categories/audiobooks/">my other audiobook posts here</a>.
Of those 3 years of books, the ones that I&rsquo;d recommend most are <strong>Success and Luck</strong> by Robert H. Frank (<a href="https://treyhunner.com/2017/01/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2016/">2016</a>), <strong>Just Mercy</strong> by Bryan Stevenson (<a href="https://treyhunner.com/2014/12/top-6-books-of-2014/">2014</a>), <strong>Whistling Vivaldi</strong> by Claude M. Steele (<a href="https://treyhunner.com/2015/12/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2015/">2015</a>), and <strong>Make it Stick</strong> by Peter C. Brown, Henry L. Roediger III, Mark A. McDaniel (<a href="https://treyhunner.com/2017/01/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2016/">2016</a>).</p>

<p>Also note that all the links above point to Goodreads, which I don&rsquo;t recommend despite the fact that I use it.
I plan to eventually switch to <a href="https://thestorygraph.com">The Story Graph</a> for recording my reading activity, but I&rsquo;m awaiting <a href="https://roadmap.thestorygraph.com/features/posts/an-api">an API</a> so I can update my current reading-tracking system (which is based around a Google Sheet totaling hours read and other stats) to use it instead of Goodreads.</p>

<h2>My favorite audiobooks of 2024</h2>

<p>I read 41 audiobooks this year.</p>

<p>These are the ones I would most recommend listening to.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Best self-help book</strong>:

<ul>
<li>Eat, Drink, and Be Healthy: The Harvard Medical School Guide to Healthy Eating</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Best page-turners</strong>:

<ul>
<li>Says Who? A Kinder, Funner Usage Guide for Everyone Who Cares About Words</li>
<li>A Little Devil in America: Notes in Praise of Black Performance</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Most thought-provoking</strong>:

<ul>
<li>Land is a Big Deal: Why rent is too high, wages too low, and what we can do about it</li>
<li>The Myth of Left and Right: How the Political Spectrum Misleads and Harms America</li>
<li>Uncommon Sense Teaching: Practical Insights in Brain Science to Help Students Learn</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Validated my current world view and I recommend read to challenge themselves</strong>:

<ul>
<li>Not the End of the World: How We Can Be the First Generation to Build a Sustainable Planet</li>
<li>Determined: A Science of Life without Free Will</li>
<li>Eating Animals</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3>Eat, Drink, and Be Healthy: The Harvard Medical School Guide to Healthy Eating</h3>

<p>This is the best book I&rsquo;ve read about nutrition.
This book contains no silver bullets; just evidence-backed advice.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this in audiobook-form, note that the last portion of the book contains recipes, read out-loud for many minutes&hellip; so I would stop listening once the recipes start.
I&rsquo;m considering buying a hard copy for some of the recipes.</p>

<h3>Says Who? A Kinder, Funner Usage Guide for Everyone Who Cares About Words</h3>

<p>This book pleased my inner wordy and challenged my inner grammando (those terms are explained in the book).</p>

<p>If you enjoy poking at the English language, I think you&rsquo;ll find this a fun listen.</p>

<h3>A Little Devil in America: Notes in Praise of Black Performance</h3>

<p>This is a beautifully written book.</p>

<p>If you enjoy writing that&rsquo;s thought-provoking, emotional, and engrossing, read/listen to this.</p>

<h3>Land is a Big Deal: Why rent is too high, wages too low, and what we can do about it</h3>

<p>This book is all about implementing a &ldquo;land value tax&rdquo; and it does a good job of explaining what that means and what the consequences might be.
A land value tax feels like an extreme marriage of capitalism and socialism, as it would (sort of) abolish private ownership of land while encouraging the market to make the best use of each piece of land.
The subject of this book is <em>very</em> wonky so this book was a bit challenging at times, but I found it fairly accessible overall.</p>

<p>For the sake of affordable housing, loosening or removing zoning restrictions (see the book Arbitrary Lines mentioned above) and reducing regulatory requirements around construction seem more important than a land value tax.
But as far as taxes go, a land value tax does seem like the most justice-oriented and efficiency-oriented tax.</p>

<h3>The Myth of Left and Right: How the Political Spectrum Misleads and Harms America</h3>

<p>I prefer a good short book to a good long book and this audiobook very much justifies the time it took to read (4 hours).</p>

<p>If you frequently talk about or think about US politics, I would recommend reading this book.
The authors make a solid case that we do a disservice to political discourse when we use the words &ldquo;left&rdquo;, &ldquo;right&rdquo;, &ldquo;liberal&rdquo;, and &ldquo;conservative&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Uncommon Sense Teaching: Practical Insights in Brain Science to Help Students Learn</h3>

<p>Much of this book was review for me: namely interleaved versus blocked practice, active versus passive learning, elaboration, and spaced repetition.
Even the parts that were review were helpful to hear again.
I also took notes from this book about &ldquo;learn it, link it&rdquo;, dopamine hits, comprehension checks, and pauses to consolidate.</p>

<p>This book included quite a bit more discussion about how the brain actually works than I remember hearing in previous books I&rsquo;ve read on learning and teaching.
It could be that these sections were simply more memorable than previous explanations I&rsquo;ve heard, as the explanations in this book heavily relied on memorable analogies and stories.</p>

<h3>Not the End of the World: How We Can Be the First Generation to Build a Sustainable Planet</h3>

<p>This book discusses what we focus on too much and too little when it comes to the problems and the solutions around climate change.
Hannah Ritchie calls out falsehoods and misconceptions, but she doesn&rsquo;t berate believers of these misconceptions.</p>

<p>We all care about solving global warming and sustainability.
Knowing more of the facts behind these concepts is the first step to working solutions.</p>

<p>This book definitely falls into the &ldquo;skepticism over cynicism&rdquo; category that I very much appreciate, as it inspires action instead of of encouraging inaction.</p>

<p>If you enjoy a Scottish accent, listen to the audiobook (Hannah Ritchie self-narrates).</p>

<h3>Determined: A Science of Life without Free Will</h3>

<p>Before reading this book, I hadn&rsquo;t considered that free will comes in shades and that as a society we have been gradually chipping away at the magnitude of free will we collectively believe in.</p>

<p>The first 9 chapters (especially 5 through 9) are a bit of a slog, as each focuses on disputing a different argument for free will.
I found the final 5 chapters (which focus on &ldquo;what do we do if there&rsquo;s no free will&rdquo;) the most interesting.</p>

<h3>Eating Animals</h3>

<p>This book was memorable in a somewhat brutal way.
I do not recommend reading this book while eating animal products, but I would recommend reading it.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s quite a bit of navel-gazing, but also quite a few interviews with many a number of folks in and around the animal farming industry.</p>

<p>For a more hopeful take on animal welfare, see the book The End of Animal Farming (mentioned above).
Also see the book Why We Love Dogs, Eat Pigs, and Wear Cows (also mentioned above)</p>

<h2>Where to buy audiobooks (not Audible)</h2>

<p>Interested in listening to these in audiobook form?</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t buy them from Audible.</p>

<p>Whenever possible, I recommend avoiding Audible because:</p>

<ol>
<li>Audible doesn&rsquo;t sell audiobooks; they sell the ability to play audiobooks through their app</li>
<li>Audible credits expire and also disappear upon cancellation, which is an awful <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_pattern">dark pattern</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Cory Doctorow has <a href="https://doctorow.medium.com/why-none-of-my-books-are-available-on-audible-83cb182f2f91">written</a> about his dislike of Audible and has recorded <a href="https://craphound.com/news/2022/07/24/why-none-of-my-books-are-available-on-audible/">an audiobook against Audible</a> (which is ironically <a href="https://www.audible.com/pd/Why-None-of-My-Books-Are-Available-on-Audible-Audiobook/B0B7KH8KSD">also on Audible</a>).</p>

<p>If you enjoy audiobooks and pro-consumer practices, I recommend trying out <a href="https://libro.fm/referral?rf_code=lfm240965">Libro.fm</a> (that&rsquo;s a referral link which will give me one free audiobook if you subscribe).</p>

<p>Unfortunately, a few of my favorite audiobooks noted above are <em>only</em> available on Audible.</p>

<p>You can purchase <em>all</em> of the above books on Libro.fm <em>except</em> for <strong>Hive Minds Give Good Hugs</strong>, <strong>Recoding America</strong>, and <strong>Walkable City</strong>.
The book <strong>Land is a Big Deal</strong> is <em>technically</em> available outside of Audible, but I&rsquo;ve only found it available for direct purchase <a href="https://www.shacksimplepress.com/product-page/copy-of-land-is-a-big-deal-audio-version">from the publisher</a> and it&rsquo;s much more expensive that way.</p>

<p>For <em>most</em> of my audiobook-listening, I subscribe to <strong>Libro.fm</strong>, checkout books from my local library with <strong>Libby</strong>, and I&rsquo;ve also used <strong>Spotify</strong> to listen to a few shorter books.
For Audible-only books, I sign up for a subscription, buy licenses until my credit balance is 0, and then cancel.</p>

<h2>Have a recommendation?</h2>

<p>Have a question?
Have an audiobook recommendation for me?</p>

<p>Comment below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Favorite Audiobooks of 2016]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2017/01/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2016/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-01T17:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2017/01/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I set a goal of listening to 40 audiobooks in 2016.  I met that goal, but just barely.  I finished exactly 40 books and one of them I actually read the old fashioned way&hellip; as an e-book!  (Philip Morgan really needs to record an audiobook of <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25754062-the-positioning-manual-for-technical-firms">The Positioning Manual</a>.)</p>

<p>I try to listen to a diverse set of books every year: I want to end my year having read books from different categories and genres and from authors with different backgrounds and writing styles.</p>

<p>I wrote about my favorite audiobooks I read in <a href="http://treyhunner.com/2015/12/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2015/">2015</a> and <a href="http://treyhunner.com/2014/12/top-6-books-of-2014/">2014</a>.  Now I&rsquo;m going to attempt the same thing for 2016.  This task is always difficult because many of these books are very different from each other so I&rsquo;m not comparing apples to apples.  But I&rsquo;m going to try my best to pick my top 6.</p>

<p>The full list of <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/year_in_books/2016/29459515">books I read in 2016 is available on my Goodreads page</a>.</p>

<h3>1. Success and Luck</h3>

<p>This book was written by an economist, but you don&rsquo;t need to know anything at all about economics to appreciate most of it.  The book is strangely (though conveniently) split into two parts: the first two-thirds of the book are very different from the last one-third.</p>

<p>During the first two-thirds of the book, Robert Frank describes the role of luck in our lives.  I believe the world view he describes can result in increased humility and happiness; it&rsquo;s a mental model of the world which encourages gratitude for your life&rsquo;s path.</p>

<p>The last one-third of the book describes a tax policy that makes quite a bit of sense once you&rsquo;ve embraced this world view.  If not you&rsquo;re into economics, feel free to skim or skip this part.  I found it pretty interesting and quite worthwhile considering it&rsquo;s only one-third of a fairly short book.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m skeptical of meritocracies, self-made people, and the idea that &ldquo;you can make it if you try&rdquo;.  If you do not share this particular brand of skepticism but you&rsquo;re curious about the reasons behind my views, read this book.  It does a great job of coherently expressing certain thoughts I&rsquo;ve had, but never been able to verbalize.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26597345-success-and-luck">Success and Luck</a> by Robert H. Frank</p>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/221484/">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by the author, Robert H. Frank</p>

<h3>2. Make it Stick</h3>

<p>My biggest career transition so far has been moving from consultant to trainer: as of mid-2015, I teach for a living.  I used to solve business problems that involved writing code, but now I focus on solving business problems that involve teaching others to write code.  I picked up Make it Stick in an effort to improve my teaching style.</p>

<p>This is one of the first books I&rsquo;ve read on pedagogy.  The book covered a lot of ground.  The authors consist of a writer (Peter C. Brown) and two cognitive scientists (Henry L. Roediger III and Mark A. McDaniel).  Together, they&rsquo;ve made a coherent book consisting of actionable advice based in research.  That&rsquo;s the big distinguishing feature of this book: it&rsquo;s research summed up for the masses.</p>

<p>This book covers the growth mindset, active retrieval, interleaved practice, spaced practice, elaboration, and other topics I&rsquo;ve forgotten the names of.  While reading this book, I frequently had ideas about how I could improve my training style.  I plan to reread this book again in 2017 as I actively incorporate ideas from this book into my training courses.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18770267-make-it-stick">Make it Stick</a> by Peter C. Brown, Henry L. Roediger III, Mark A. McDaniel</p>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/158926/">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Qarie Marshall</p>

<h3>3. The Brain Audit</h3>

<p>I believe this is the first audiobook I&rsquo;ve listened to twice.  I listened to it early in the year while on a family vacation and then listened to it a few months later while struggling to apply some of the ideas from this book to my business.</p>

<p>This is not just a business book.  I&rsquo;ve found this book valuable when promoting my Python chats, tweeting about charitable and non-profit events, and even writing blog posts.</p>

<p>The Brain Audit really changed the way I look at my business, my writing, and sales &amp; marketing in general.  Most importantly, it included a ton of actionable advice.  Sean D'Souza does give some general advice but he definitely gets very specific with some of his advice, which I really appreciated.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10417944-the-brain-audit">The Brain Audit</a> by Sean D'Souza</p>

<p><a href="https://www.psychotactics.com/brain-audit-audio-book/">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by the author, Sean D'Souza</p>

<h3>4. How to Be Black</h3>

<p>I read this book before realizing that I&rsquo;ve seen Baratunde participating in the CodeNewbies Twitter chats.</p>

<p>I did not know what this book was about when I picked it up and the book started as a satirical instruction manual of sorts which both confused and amused me.  The majority of the book was a memoir punctuated by life lessons and questions answered by a panel of &ldquo;experts&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The book pokes fun at the notion of categorizing people by blackness, but it does so while staying grounded in the reality of our race-aware world.  The asides between Baratunde&rsquo;s story included groan-worthy truths, ideas pushed to ridiculous ends, and a lot of humor wrapped around both light and heavy subjects.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12959743-how-to-be-black">How to Be Black</a> by Baratunde Thurston</p>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/96254/">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by the author, Baratunde Thurston</p>

<h3>5. The Art of Asking</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m likely biased in my enjoyment for this book by the fact that I like Amanda Palmer&rsquo;s music and I appreciated watching interviews and talks from her before reading her book.</p>

<p>This is not a self help book: this is really more of a themed memoir.  I really enjoyed hearing Amanda Palmer&rsquo;s story and I especially enjoyed hearing her read her own work.  She narrates very well and the occasional musical interludes made the book even more special to me.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20980987-the-art-of-asking-or-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-let-people-hel">The Art of Asking</a> by Amanda Palmer</p>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/178890/">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by the author, Amanda Palmer</p>

<h3>6. The Beautiful Struggle</h3>

<p>This is non-fiction, but the scenes stuck with me like it was fiction.  Ta-Nehisi Coates' told the story of his childhood beautifully.  This was very well-written and the audiobook was well-narrated.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2784926-the-beautiful-struggle">The Beautiful Struggle</a> by Ta-Nehisi Coates</p>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/224786/">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by J.D. Jackson</p>

<h3>More books</h3>

<p>After compiling this list I realized a few interesting things:</p>

<ul>
<li>All of the books are available DRM-free (this wasn&rsquo;t true for my 2014 and 2015 lists)</li>
<li>Most of the books are narrated by the authors, which is slightly uncommon</li>
<li>All of these books are non-fiction</li>
</ul>


<p>Usually I mix in some fiction, so I&rsquo;ll recommend some of the fiction I read now.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re looking for historical fiction try <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14891.A_Tree_Grows_in_Brooklyn">A Tree Grows in Brooklyn</a>, <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/230996.Wild_Ginger">Wild Ginger</a>, or <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18749.Half_of_a_Yellow_Sun">Half of a Yellow Sun</a>.  If you&rsquo;re looking for science fiction or fantasy try <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/115969.Overclocked">Overclocked</a>, <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14497.Neverwhere">Neverwhere</a>, or <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/9969571-ready-player-one">Ready Player One</a>.</p>

<p>Now for this year&rsquo;s reading goal!  I&rsquo;m going to be a little less ambitious this year.  I plan to listen to more long audiobooks, so I&rsquo;ve lowered my reading goal drastically.  In 2017 <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user_challenges/7102421">I plan to read 24 books</a>, all of them likely audiobooks.  Feel free to <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/29459515-trey-hunner">follow me on Goodreads</a> if you&rsquo;d like to keep up with my reading habits.</p>

<p>What good audiobooks have you listened to?  Have any recommendations for me?  Please share them with me on Goodreads, tweet at me, email me, or comment below!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My favorite audiobooks of 2015]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2015/12/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-31T07:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2015/12/my-favorite-audiobooks-of-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I set a goal of listening to 50 audiobooks in 2015 and I met this goal.  I listened to over 400 hours of audiobooks &ndash; that&rsquo;s over 1 hour of listening per day.</p>

<p>I make an effort to listen to audiobooks that challenge me.  I try to read books by people from different backgrounds, books from genres I&rsquo;m unaccustomed to, and books on subjects that challenge my world views.</p>

<p>This list only represents 10 of my favorite listens from this year.  You can find a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/year_in_books/2015/29459515">full list of the books I read in 2015 on my Goodreads page</a>.</p>

<h3>1. How to Slowly Kill Yourself and Others in America</h3>

<p>This book meanders through heavy issues, including exceptionalism, misogyny, and dying young.  Kanye, Obama, and Tupac all make appearances.  This is some of the most eloquent and addictive prose I&rsquo;ve heard: witty and grave.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17290919-how-to-slowly-kill-yourself-and-others-in-america">How to Slowly Kill Yourself and Others in America</a> by Kiese Laymon</li>
<li><a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/Nonfiction/How-to-Slowly-Kill-Yourself-and-Others-in-America-Audiobook/B00S5AAG1K/ref=a_search_c4_1_1_srTtl">Audible audiobook</a> read by Kevin Free</li>
</ul>


<h3>2. Whistling Vivaldi</h3>

<p>Even in the seeming absence of individual and institutional discrimination, we can be affected by stereotype threats.  Identity threat is a real problem.  If you help lead an organization of people, you should read this book or at least read a good summary of it.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6649312-whistling-vivaldi">Whistling Vivaldi</a> by Claude M. Steele</li>
<li><a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/Nonfiction/Whistling-Vivaldi-Audiobook/B00CJ0I41Q/ref=a_search_c4_1_1_srTtl">Audible audiobook</a> read by DeMario Clarke</li>
</ul>


<h3>3. Americanah</h3>

<p>The main character, Ifemelu, is a complex individual who struggles with romance, family, and identity.  I really enjoyed this story and I especially enjoyed Adjoa Andoh&rsquo;s audiobook narration.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15796700-americanah">Americanah</a> by Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie</li>
<li><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/135855">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Adjoa Andoh</li>
</ul>


<h3>4. The Righteous Mind</h3>

<p>We tend to categorize ourselves based on which moral pillars we hold sacred and which we ignore.  It is difficult but important to empathize with those who recognize different moral pillars than you.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11324722-the-righteous-mind">The Righteous Mind</a> by Jonathan Haidt</li>
<li><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/100887">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Jonathan Haidt</li>
</ul>


<h3>5. The New Jim Crow</h3>

<p>This book discusses the effects of the war on drugs, rising incarceration rates, affirmative action, color-blindness, and a number of other issues.  I learned quite a few eye-opening facts while reading.  Take a break from Law and Order and listen to this book instead.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6792458-the-new-jim-crow">The New Jim Crow</a> by Michelle Alexander</li>
<li><a href="http://www.downpour.com/the-new-jim-crow-1">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Karen Chilton</li>
</ul>


<h3>6. Reading Lolita in Tehran</h3>

<p>In this book we reflect upon Iranian life through nineteenth and twentieth century literature.  Culture and politics are discussed in the context of the books studied in a secret book club.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7603.Reading_Lolita_in_Tehran">Reading Lolita in Tehran</a> by Azar Nafisi</li>
<li><a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/Bios-Memoirs/Reading-Lolita-in-Tehran-Audiobook/B002V0ABTC/ref=a_search_c4_1_1_srTtl">Audible audiobook</a> read by Lisette Lecat</li>
</ul>


<h3>7. Twelve Years a Slave</h3>

<p>This autobiography was very clear, very event-filled, and overall I found it very well-written.  I had less trouble keeping track of the characters than in much of the fiction I read.  I haven&rsquo;t seen the movie yet, but I&rsquo;m hoping it&rsquo;s as good as the book.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18478222-twelve-years-a-slave">Twelve Years a Slave</a> by Solomon Northup</li>
<li><a href="http://www.downpour.com/twelve-years-a-slave-1">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Louis Gossett, Jr.</li>
</ul>


<h3>8. The Wordy Shipmates</h3>

<p>This journey through history included religion, politics, and drama with tie-ins to modern culture and a smattering of humor.  I didn&rsquo;t understand much of this book, but I did really enjoy it.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2845287-the-wordy-shipmates">The Wordy Shipmates</a> by Sarah Vowell</li>
<li><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/93953">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Sarah Vowell</li>
</ul>


<h3>9. The Handmaid&rsquo;s Tale</h3>

<p>Some people call this book &ldquo;science fiction&rdquo;.  I&rsquo;d call it fiction set in the future, a relatable and frightening future.  This dystopian patriarchy is fueled by religious extremism and a fertility problem.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/38447.The_Handmaid_s_Tale">The Handmaid&rsquo;s Tale</a> by Margaret Atwood</li>
<li><a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/Fiction/The-Handmaids-Tale-Audiobook/B008NB9GIU/ref=a_search_c4_1_1_srTtl">Audible audiobook</a> read by Claire Danes</li>
</ul>


<h3>10. For the Win</h3>

<p>This book focuses on abuse of workers around the world.  It doesn&rsquo;t focus on technology or corruption, unlike other Doctorow books I&rsquo;ve read.  The protagonists (there were many) seemed less stereotypical than the protagonist in Little Brother.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7241373-for-the-win">For the Win</a> by Cory Doctorow</li>
<li><a href="http://craphound.com/ftw/for-the-win-audiobook/">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by George Newbern</li>
</ul>


<h3>Bonus</h3>

<p>Need more than 10 audiobook recommendations?  Here&rsquo;s five more.</p>

<h4>1. Between the World and Me</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25489625-between-the-world-and-me">Between the World and Me</a> by Ta-Nehisi Coates</li>
<li><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/198859">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Ta-Nehisi Coates</li>
</ul>


<h4>2. The Truth is a Cave in the Black Mountains</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18635092-the-truth-is-a-cave-in-the-black-mountains">The Truth is a Cave in the Black Mountains</a> by Neil Gaiman</li>
<li><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/157874">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Neil Gaiman</li>
</ul>


<h4>3. The Woman Warrior</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/30852.The_Woman_Warrior">The Woman Warrior</a> by Maxine Hong Kingston</li>
<li><a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/Bios-Memoirs/The-Woman-Warrior-Audiobook/B004HMEXGE/ref=a_search_c4_1_2_srTtl">Audible audiobook</a> read by Ming-Na</li>
</ul>


<h4>4. Information Doesn&rsquo;t Want to Be Free</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20763766-information-doesn-t-want-to-be-free">Information Doesn&rsquo;t Want to Be Free</a> by Cory Doctorow</li>
<li><a href="http://craphound.com/news/2014/12/10/information-doesnt-want-to-be-free-audiobook/">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Wil Wheaton</li>
</ul>


<h4>5. For All the Tea in China</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3081255-for-all-the-tea-in-china">For All the Tea in China</a> by Sarah Rose</li>
<li><a href="http://www.downpour.com/for-all-the-tea-in-china-1">DRM-free audiobook</a> read by Sarah Rose</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Top 6 Audiobooks of 2014]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2014/12/top-6-books-of-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-20T12:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2014/12/top-6-books-of-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I rarely read books.  I tend to lose my place after putting books down for too long and I&rsquo;m generally a slow and easily-distracted reader.</p>

<p>I discovered audiobooks this year and it has reintroduced me to long-form books, both fiction and non-fiction.  I have listened to about one book a week for the last 9 months.</p>

<h2>&ldquo;Just Mercy&rdquo; by Bryan Stevenson</h2>

<h4>Content</h4>

<p>In this book, Bryan Stevenson retells stories about the founding of the Equal Justice Initiative as well as some of the cases he worked on, focusing primarily on the case of Walter McMillian.  This book was engrossing, hope-filled, and crushing at times.  I had given little thought to the inner-workings of our justice system before reading this book.</p>

<h4>Narration</h4>

<p>I really enjoyed Bryan Stevenson&rsquo;s self-narration.  He isn&rsquo;t a particularly animated orator, but he tells a story well and I never caught myself dozing off.</p>

<h4>Links</h4>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/catalog/product/view/id/163963">Downpour (DRM-free) link</a>
<a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/Bios-Memoirs/Just-Mercy-Audiobook/B00O4FH8E8/ref=a_search_c4_1_1_srTtl?qid=1418343414&amp;sr=1-1">Audible link</a></p>

<h2>&ldquo;Little Brother&rdquo; by Cory Doctorow</h2>

<h4>Content</h4>

<p>This reads like a modern 1984.  The science fiction was minimal and the reactions of the public and the government felt fairly believable.</p>

<p>This is the first book in the Little Brother trilogy.  I enjoyed the first book the most.  The last book didn&rsquo;t serve much purpose except to wrap up the series.</p>

<h4>Narration</h4>

<p>I enjoyed Kirby Heyborne&rsquo;s narration and character voices.  In comparison, Wil Wheaton&rsquo;s reading of Homeland (book 2 of the trilogy) was animated, but he pronounced some names strangely.  I liked Cory Doctorow&rsquo;s reading of Lawful Interception (book 3) the most out of the three books in the series.</p>

<h4>Links</h4>

<p><a href="http://craphound.com/?p=4199">Purchase link on Doctorow&rsquo;s website</a>
<a href="http://www.downpour.com/little-brother-1">Downpour link</a></p>

<h2>&ldquo;Lesterland&rdquo; by Lawrence Lessig</h2>

<h4>Content</h4>

<p>Lawrence Lessig explains a core problem in our democratic republic: the way we fund political campaigns.  For a summary of the book, check out his <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/lawrence_lessig_we_the_people_and_the_republic_we_must_reclaim">TED talk</a> on the same topic.</p>

<h4>Narration</h4>

<p>I enjoyed Lawrence Lessig&rsquo;s self-narration.  It was like listening to an extended version of his <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/lawrence_lessig_we_the_people_and_the_republic_we_must_reclaim">TED talk</a>.</p>

<h4>Links</h4>

<p><a href="https://archive.org/details/Lesterland">Free download link</a>
<a href="http://lesterland.lessig.org/">The USA is Lesterland website</a></p>

<h2>&ldquo;The Martian&rdquo; by Andy Weir</h2>

<h4>Content</h4>

<p>Astronaut Mark Watney struggles to survive on Mars after a dust storm nearly kills him and causes his crew to evacuate after they assume he died.  Watney&rsquo;s ingenuity, luck, and sense of humor made this an enjoyable read.  The science sounded mostly plausible also.</p>

<h4>Narration</h4>

<p>I enjoyed R. C. Brady&rsquo;s narration of Mark Watney&rsquo;s dark humor.</p>

<h4>Links</h4>

<p><a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/Sci-Fi-Fantasy/The-Martian-Audiobook/B00B5HZGUG/">Audible link</a></p>

<h2>&ldquo;A Short History of Nearly Everything&rdquo; by Bill Bryson</h2>

<h4>Content</h4>

<p>This book crams in a lot of facts as well as historical context.  It does meander quite a bit, but I really enjoyed it.</p>

<h4>Narration</h4>

<p>Richard Matthew has a very soothing voice.  I really enjoyed listening to this book while on vacation and while falling asleep.</p>

<p>There is also an abridged version of this book read by the author.  I haven&rsquo;t listened to the abridged version, but I did enjoy the author&rsquo;s reading of &ldquo;At Home&rdquo;.  Bill Bryson reads well, but his voice isn&rsquo;t nearly as soothing as Richard Matthew&rsquo;s.</p>

<h4>Links</h4>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/a-short-history-of-nearly-everything-1">Downpour link</a>
<a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/History/A-Short-History-of-Nearly-Everything-Audiobook/B002V0KFPW/">Audible link</a></p>

<h2>&ldquo;You Are Not So Smart&rdquo; by David McRaney</h2>

<h4>Content</h4>

<p>This book is packed with common self-delusions.  Unfortunately, most delusions do not come with solutions attached, but sometimes just knowing about a delusion can help make your world view slightly more realistic.</p>

<h4>Narration</h4>

<p>Don Hagen&rsquo;s narration is fairly dry, but it works well with the tone of the book.</p>

<h3>Links</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/you-are-not-so-smart-1">Downpour link</a>
<a href="http://www.audible.com/pd/Nonfiction/You-Are-Not-So-Smart-Audiobook/B006K4GN56/">Audible link</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CLI for finding DRM-free Audiobooks]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2014/05/cli-for-finding-drm-free-audiobooks/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-14T12:31:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2014/05/cli-for-finding-drm-free-audiobooks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently acquired an appreciation for audiobooks.  I listen to multiple
audiobooks every month and I prefer DRM-free audiobooks so that I can listen
through my favorite audiobook reader on each of my devices.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.downpour.com/">Downpour</a> and <a href="http://www.emusic.com/">eMusic</a> are the only services I know that provide a large
selection of DRM-free audiobooks.  Unfortunately not all audiobooks are
available on either of these sites, so I often end up searching both sites for
each book to discover what versions (if any) are available from each.  I got
sick of searching both websites all the time, so I just created a Python script
to do that work for me.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/21f307b975027be5162d.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/usr/bin/env python
&quot;&quot;&quot;
Search downpour.com and emusic.com for DRM-free audiobooks

Usage::

    ./find_audiobooks.py &lt;title&gt;...

File released to the public domain under CC0 license:
http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/deed

Requires purl and beautifulsoup4::

    $ pip install purl beautifulsoup4

&quot;&quot;&quot;
from __future__ import unicode_literals
import sys
from itertools import chain, izip_longest
import urllib2

from bs4 import BeautifulSoup
from purl import URL


def unescape(text):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Return string without smart apostrophes&quot;&quot;&quot;
    return text.replace(&#39;\u2019&#39;, &quot;&#39;&quot;)


def get_downpour_url(book_name):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Return search URL for downpour.com&quot;&quot;&quot;
    base = URL(&quot;http://www.downpour.com/catalogsearch/result/&quot;)
    return base.query_param(&#39;q&#39;, book_name).as_string()


def get_emusic_url(book_name):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Return search URL for emusic.com&quot;&quot;&quot;
    base_url = URL(&quot;http://www.emusic.com/search/book/&quot;)
    return base_url.query_param(&#39;s&#39;, book_name).as_string()


def search_downpour(book_name):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Search Downpour and return list of parsed results&quot;&quot;&quot;
    response = urllib2.urlopen(get_downpour_url(book_name))
    page = BeautifulSoup(response)
    books = page.find_all(&#39;li&#39;, attrs={&#39;class&#39;: &quot;item&quot;})
    results = []
    for book in books:
        header = book.find(attrs={&#39;class&#39;: &quot;product-name&quot;})
        link_tag = header.find(&#39;a&#39;)
        title = &#39; &#39;.join(unescape(x)
                         for x in link_tag.stripped_strings)
        link = link_tag[&#39;href&#39;]
        for node in book.find_all(attrs={&#39;class&#39;: &#39;author&#39;}):
            author_text = node.text
            if author_text.startswith(&#39;By&#39;):
                author = author_text[2:].strip()
        results.append({
            &#39;title&#39;: title,
            &#39;link&#39;: link,
            &#39;author&#39;: author,
        })
    return results


def search_emusic(book_name):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Search eMusic and return list of parsed results&quot;&quot;&quot;
    response = urllib2.urlopen(get_emusic_url(book_name))
    page = BeautifulSoup(response)
    books = page.find_all(&#39;li&#39;, attrs={&#39;class&#39;: &quot;bundle&quot;})
    results = []
    for book in books:
        link_tag = book.find(&#39;h4&#39;).find(&#39;a&#39;)
        author_tag = book.find(&#39;h5&#39;)
        results.append({
            &#39;title&#39;: link_tag.text,
            &#39;link&#39;: link_tag[&#39;href&#39;],
            &#39;author&#39;: author_tag.text,
        })
    return results


def print_result(result):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Print title, author, and link for audiobook result&quot;&quot;&quot;
    print &quot;Title: {}&quot;.format(result[&#39;title&#39;])
    print &quot;Author: {}&quot;.format(result[&#39;author&#39;])
    print &quot;Link: {}&quot;.format(result[&#39;link&#39;])
    print


def merge_lists(*lists):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Return merge of lists by alternating elements of each&quot;&quot;&quot;
    combined_lists = chain.from_iterable(izip_longest(*lists))
    return list(filter(bool, combined_lists))


def main(*args):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Search audiobook sites and return search results&quot;&quot;&quot;
    for book_name in args:
        results1 = search_downpour(book_name)
        results2 = search_emusic(book_name)
        results = merge_lists(results1[:3], results2[:3])
        for result in results:
            print_result(result)


if __name__ == &quot;__main__&quot;:
    main(*sys.argv[1:])
</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<h3>Future Improvements</h3>

<p>Some ideas for future improvements:</p>

<ul>
<li>Add <a href="http://www.audible.com/">Audible</a> results when the book cannot be found in a DRM-free format</li>
<li>Rewrite the script in JavaScript and create a Chrome extension out of it</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://github.com/kennethreitz/clint">clint</a> to colorize the command-line output</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
