<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: python | Trey Hunner]]></title>
  <link href="https://treyhunner.com/blog/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://treyhunner.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-11-27T18:49:28-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://treyhunner.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Trey Hunner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python Black Friday &amp; Cyber Monday sales (2025)]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2025/11/python-black-friday-and-cyber-monday-sales-2025/"/>
    <updated>2025-11-24T09:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2025/11/python-black-friday-and-cyber-monday-sales-2025</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s time for some <strong>discounted</strong> Python-related skill-building.
This is my <strong><a href="https://treyhunner.com/blog/categories/sales/">eighth annual compilation</a></strong> of Python learning-related Black Friday &amp; Cyber Monday deals.
If you find a Python-related deal in the next week that isn&rsquo;t on this list, please contact me.</p>

<h2>Python-related sales</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not even Black Friday yet, but most of these Python-related Black Friday sales are <strong>already live</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/lifetime-access-sale">Python Morsels</a></strong>: I&rsquo;m offering <strong>lifetime access</strong> for the second time ever (more details below)</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://courses.dataschool.io/pass">Data School</a></strong>: a new subscription to access all of Kevin&rsquo;s <strong>7 courses plus all upcoming courses</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="http://talkpython.fm/black-friday">Talk Python</a></strong>: AI Python bundle, the Everything Bundle, and Michael&rsquo;s Talk Python in Production</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://lernerpython.com/pricing/">Reuven Lerner</a></strong>: get 20% off <strong>your first year</strong> of the <strong>LernerPython+data</strong> tier (code <code>BF2025</code>)</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://pythontest.com/2025-black-friday/">Brian Okken</a></strong>: get 50% off his pytest books and courses (code <code>SAVE50</code>)</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://mathspp.gumroad.com/l/all-books-bundle/BF202550">Rodrigo</a></strong>: get 50% off all his books including his all books bundle (code <code>BF202550</code>)</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.blog.pythonlibrary.org/2025/11/18/black-friday-python-deals-came-early/">Mike Driscoll</a></strong>: get 50% off all his <strong>Python books and courses</strong> (code <code>BLACKISBACK</code>)</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://thepythoncodingplace.thinkific.com/bundles/the-python-coding-place-membership?coupon=black50">The Python Coding Place</a></strong>: get 50% the <strong>all course bundle</strong> of 12 courses</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://learnbyexample.gumroad.com/l/all-books/FestiveOffer">Sundeep Agarwal</a></strong>: ~55% off Sundeep&rsquo;s <strong>all books bundle</strong> with code <code>FestiveOffer</code></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://nodeledge.ai/learn/paths/essential-python-for-data-science-and-ml">Nodeledge</a></strong>: get 20% off your first payment (code <code>BF2025</code>)</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/online-learning/2025-cyber-sale.html?code=CYBERSAVE25">O'Reilly Media</a></strong>: 40% off <strong>the first year</strong> with code <code>CYBERWEEK25</code> ($299 instead of $499)</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.manning.com/catalog/programming-languages-and-styles/python">Manning</a></strong> is offering 50% off from Nov 25 to Dec 1</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://mastodon.social/@b0rk@jvns.ca/115571664177415123">Wizard Zines</a></strong>: 50% all of Julia Evan&rsquo;s <em>great</em> <strong>zines on various tech topics</strong> that I personally find both fun and useful (not Python-related, but one of my favorite annual sales)&hellip; this is a one-day Black Friday exclusive sale</li>
</ul>


<!--
Likely additional sales:

- **[Brian Okken](https://courses.pythontest.com)**
- **[Matt Harrison][]**
- **[Rodrigo][]**
- **[Test Driven][]**
- **[Pragmatic Bookshelf][]**
- **[No Starch][]**
- **[Manning][]**
-->


<p>I will be keeping an idea on other potential sales and updating this post as I find them.
If you&rsquo;ve seen a sale that I haven&rsquo;t, please contact me or comment below.</p>

<h2>Django-related sales</h2>

<p>Adam Johnson has also published a list of <a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/">Django-related deals for Black Friday</a> (which he&rsquo;s been doing for a few years now).
I&rsquo;ve included links below to the different sections in Adam&rsquo;s post&hellip;</p>

<p>Courses and books:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#my-books">Adam&rsquo;s books</a>: his books and bundles on Django, Git, and GitHub DX and Django test performance are all 50% off</li>
<li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#learndjango-com-course-bundle">LearnDjango.com course bundle</a>: Will Vincent is offering 50% off his 3 courses</li>
<li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#django-5-by-example">Django 5 By Example</a>: 30% off this book by Antonio Melé</li>
<li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#django-in-action">Django in Action</a>: 50% off this book by Christopher Trudeau</li>
<li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#async-patterns-in-django">Async Patterns in Django</a>: 50% off this book by Paul Bailey</li>
</ul>


<p>Packages related to Django:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#aidas-bendoraitis-paid-packages">Aidas Bendoraitis</a>: has 3 Django packages available at a 20% discount</li>
<li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#appliku">Appliku</a>: 30% of annual plans for this Django deployment tool</li>
<li><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#saas-pegasus">Saas Pegasus</a>: 50% off the unlimited license for this configurable Django project template</li>
</ul>


<p>Adam also gives a shout out to <a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2025/11/20/django-black-friday-deals-2025/#bonus-django-itself">sponsoring Django itself</a>.</p>

<h2>More on my sale: Python Morsels Lifetime Access</h2>

<p>Python Morsels is a hands-on, <strong>exercise-driven</strong> Python skill-building platform designed to help developers <strong>write cleaner, more idiomatic Python</strong> through real-world practice.
This growing library of exercises, videos, and courses is aimed primarily at intermediate and professional developers.
If you haven&rsquo;t used Python Morsels, you can read about it <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2025/11/lifetime-access-sale-2025/">in my sale announcement post</a>.</p>

<p>This Black Friday / Cyber Monday, I&rsquo;m offering <a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/lifetime-access-sale">lifetime access</a>: all current and future content for in a single payment.
If you&rsquo;d like to build confidence in your everyday Python skills, consider this sale.
It&rsquo;s <strong>about 50% cheaper than paying annually for five years</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="https://pythonmorsels.com/lifetime-access-sale/" class="subscribe-btn form-big">Get lifetime access to Python Morsels</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python Morsels Lifetime Access Sale]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2025/11/lifetime-access-sale-2025/"/>
    <updated>2025-11-21T14:42:36-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2025/11/lifetime-access-sale-2025</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you code in Python regularly, you&rsquo;re already learning new things everyday.</p>

<p>You hit a wall, or something breaks. Then you search around, spend some hours on Stack Overflow, and eventually, you figure it out.</p>

<p><strong>But this kind of learning is unstructured. It&rsquo;s reactive, instead of intentional.</strong></p>

<p>You fix the problem at hand, but the underlying gaps in your knowledge remain unaddressed.</p>

<h2>A more structured way to improve your Python skills</h2>

<p>Python Morsels gives you <strong>a structured, hands-on way to improve your Python skills</strong> through weekly practice:</p>

<ul>
<li>Notice significant progress with as little as 30 minutes a week</li>
<li>Learn to naturally think more Pythonically</li>
<li>Explore new approaches to problem-solving</li>
<li>Challenge yourself to get outside your comfort zone regularly</li>
</ul>


<p>Python Morsels is a subscription service because <strong>I&rsquo;m adding new learning resources almost every week</strong>.</p>

<p>But through December 1st, you can get <strong><a href="https://pythonmorsels.com/lifetime-access-sale/">lifetime access</a></strong> for a one-time payment.</p>

<h2>How it works</h2>

<p>When you sign up for Python Morsels, you&rsquo;ll choose your current Python skill level, from novice to advanced.</p>

<p>Based on your skill level, <strong>each Monday I&rsquo;ll send you a personalized routine</strong> with:</p>

<ul>
<li>a short screencast to watch (or read)</li>
<li>a multi-part exercise to move you outside your comfort zone</li>
<li>a mini exercise that you can accomplish in just 10 minutes</li>
<li>links to dive deeper into subsequent screencasts and exercises</li>
</ul>


<p>Think of Python Morsels as a gym for your Python skills: you come in for quick training sessions, put in the reps, and make a little more progress each time.</p>

<p>All these resources are accessible to you forever, and with lifetime access you&rsquo;ll never pay another subscription fee.</p>

<h2>What Python Morsels includes</h2>

<p>Python Morsels has grown a lot over the past 8 years. Currently, Python Morsels has:</p>

<ul>
<li>235+ Video Lessons (or screencasts, as I call them)</li>
<li>262+ Hands-On Exercises (with solution walkthroughs)</li>
<li>500+ Optional Bonuses (to challenge every skill level)</li>
<li>303+ Articles Organized Topic-Wise (if you prefer reading)</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ll be sending you personalized recommendations every week, but you can use these resources however they fit your routine: as learning guides, hands-on practice sessions, quick cheatsheets, long-term reference material, or quick Python workouts.</p>

<p>In addition to this, Python Morsels also gives you access to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Python Jumpstart - a structured course for beginners</li>
<li>Additional Deep-Dive Courses - structured tracks to master a concept</li>
<li>Exercise Paths - topic-based exercises to strengthen a specific skill</li>
</ul>


<p>Because Python Morsels runs as an active subscription service, I&rsquo;m always adding new screencasts, new exercises, and updated material on a weekly or monthly cycle. I also keep everything up-to-date with each new Python release, incorporating newly added features and retiring end-of-life&rsquo;d Python versions.</p>

<h2>Lock in lifetime access</h2>

<p>Python Morsels usually costs <strong>$240/year</strong> but you can get <strong>lifetime access</strong> through December 1st for a one-time payment. I&rsquo;ve only offered lifetime access <strong>once before</strong> in 8 years.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve been on the fence about subscribing to Python Morsels or want to invest in building a daily learning habit, this is a good time to do it.</p>

<p><a href="https://pythonmorsels.com/lifetime-access-sale/" class="subscribe-btn form-big">Get lifetime access to Python Morsels</a></p>

<p>If you have questions about the sale, please comment below or <a href="mailto:he&amp;#108;p&amp;#64;&amp;#112;%7&amp;#57;th%6Fnmo&amp;#114;s%6&amp;#53;ls&amp;#46;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;m">email me</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Handy Python REPL Modifications]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2025/10/handy-python-repl-modifications/"/>
    <updated>2025-10-08T19:59:20-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2025/10/handy-python-repl-modifications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I find myself in the Python REPL <em>a lot</em>.</p>

<p>I open up the REPL to play with an idea, to use Python as a calculator or quick and dirty text parsing tool, to record a screencast, to come up with a code example for an article, and (most importantly for me) to teach Python.
My Python courses and workshops are based largely around writing code together to guess how something works, try it out, and repeat.</p>

<p>As I&rsquo;ve written about before, you can <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2024/10/adding-keyboard-shortcuts-to-the-python-repl/">add custom keyboard shortcuts</a> to the new Python REPL (since 3.13) and <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2025/09/customizing-your-python-repl-color-scheme/">customize the REPL syntax highlighting</a> (since 3.14).
If you spend time in the Python REPL and wish it behaved a little more <strong>like your favorite editor</strong>, these tricks can come in handy.</p>

<p>I have added <strong>custom keyboard shortcuts</strong> to my REPL and other modifications to help me <strong>more quickly write and edit code in my REPL</strong>.
I&rsquo;d like to share some of the modifications that I&rsquo;ve found helpful in my own Python REPL.</p>

<h2>Creating a PYTHONSTARTUP file</h2>

<p>If you want to run Python code every time an interactive prompt (a REPL) starts, you can make a PYTHONSTARTUP file.</p>

<p>When Python launches an interactive prompt, it checks for a <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> environment variable.
If it finds one, it treats it as a filename that contains Python code and it <strong>runs all the code in that file</strong>, as if you had copy-pasted the code into the REPL.</p>

<p>So all of the modifications I have made to my Python REPL rely on this <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> variable in my <code>~/.zshenv</code> file:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">export PYTHONSTARTUP=$HOME/.startup.py
</code></pre>

<p>If you use bash, you&rsquo;ll put that in your <code>~/.bashrc</code> file.
If you&rsquo;re on Windows <a href="https://gist.github.com/mitchmindtree/92c8e37fa80c8dddee5b94fc88d1288b">you&rsquo;ll need to set an environment variable the Windows way</a>.</p>

<p>With that variable set, I can now create a <code>~/.startup.py</code> file that has Python code in it.
That code will automatically run every time I launch a new Python REPL, whether within a virtual environment or outside of one.</p>

<h2>My REPL keyboard shortcuts</h2>

<p>The quick summary of my <em>current</em> modifications are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pressing <strong>Home</strong> moves to the <strong>first character in the code block</strong></li>
<li>Pressing <strong>End</strong> moves to the <strong>last character in the code block</strong></li>
<li>Pressing <strong>Alt+M</strong> moves to the <strong>first character</strong> on the current line</li>
<li>Pressing <strong>Shift+Tab</strong> removes <strong>common indentation</strong> from the code block</li>
<li>Pressing <strong>Alt+Up</strong> swaps the current line with <strong>the line above it</strong></li>
<li>Pressing <strong>Alt+Down</strong> swaps the current line with <strong>the line below it</strong></li>
<li>Pressing <strong>Ctrl+N</strong> inserts <strong>a specific list of numbers</strong></li>
<li>Pressing <strong>Ctrl+F</strong> inserts <strong>a specific list of strings</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>If you&rsquo;ve read <a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/repl-features/">my Python REPL shortcuts</a> article, you know that we can use <strong>Ctrl+A</strong> to move to the beginning of the line and <strong>Ctrl+E</strong> to move to the end of the line.
I already use those instead of the Home and End keys, so I decided to rebind Home and End to do something different.</p>

<p>The <strong>Alt+M</strong> key combination is essentially the same as <code>Alt+M</code> in Emacs or <code>^</code> in Vim. I usually prefer to move to the beginning of the non-whitespace in a line rather than to the beginning of the <em>entire</em> line.</p>

<p>The <strong>Shift+Tab</strong> functionality is basically a fancy wrapper around <a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/dedent/">using <code>textwrap.dedent</code></a>: it dedents the current code block while keeping the cursor over the same character it was at before.</p>

<p>The <strong>Ctrl+N</strong> and <strong>Ctrl+F</strong> shortcuts make it easier for me to grab an example data structure to work with when teaching.</p>

<p>In addition to the above changes, I also modify my color scheme to work nicely with my Solarized Light color scheme in Vim.</p>

<h2>I created a pyrepl-hacks library for this</h2>

<p>My PYTHONSTARTUP file became so messy that I ended up creating a <a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/pyrepl-hacks">pyrepl-hacks library</a> to help me with these modifications.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/dotfiles/commits/main/startup.py">My PYTHONSTARTUP file</a> now looks pretty much like this:</p>

<pre><code class="python">import pathlib as _pathlib, sys as _sys
_sys.path.append(str(_pathlib.Path.home() / ".pyhacks"))

try:
    import pyrepl_hacks as _repl
except ImportError:
    _repl = None  # We're on Python 3.12 or below
else:
    _repl.bind("Home", "home")
    _repl.bind("End", "end")
    _repl.bind("Alt+M", "move-to-indentation")
    _repl.bind("Shift+Tab", "dedent")
    _repl.bind("Alt+Down", "move-line-down")
    _repl.bind("Alt+Up", "move-line-up")
    _repl.bind_to_insert("Ctrl+N", "[2, 1, 3, 4, 7, 11, 18, 29]")
    _repl.bind_to_insert(
        "Ctrl+F",
        '["apples", "oranges", "bananas", "strawberries", "pears"]',
    )

    try:
        # Solarized Light theme to match vim
        _repl.update_theme(
            keyword="green",
            builtin="blue",
            comment="intense blue",
            string="cyan",
            number="cyan",
            definition="blue",
            soft_keyword="bold green",
            op="intense green",
            reset="reset, intense green",
        )
    except ImportError:
        pass  # We're on Python 3.13 or below

del _repl, _pathlib, _sys  # Avoid global REPL namespace pollution
</code></pre>

<p>That&rsquo;s pretty short!</p>

<p>But wait&hellip; won&rsquo;t this fail unless pyrepl-hacks is installed in every virtual environment <em>and</em> installed globally for every Python version on my machine?</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s where that <code>sys.path.append</code> trick comes in handy&hellip;</p>

<h2>Wait&hellip; let&rsquo;s acknowledge the dragons 🐲</h2>

<p>At this point I&rsquo;d like to pause to note that all of this relies on using an implementation detail of Python that is deliberately undocumented because it <em>is not designed</em> to be used by end users.</p>

<p>The above code all relies on the <code>_pyrepl</code> module that was added in Python 3.13 (and optionally the <code>_colorize</code> module that was added in Python 3.14).</p>

<p>When I run a new future version of Python (for example Python 3.15) this solution may break.
I&rsquo;m willing to take that risk, as I know that I can always unset my shell&rsquo;s <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> variable or clear out my startup file.</p>

<p>So, just be aware&hellip; here be (private undocumented implementation detail) dragons.</p>

<h2>Monkey patching <code>sys.path</code> to allow importing <code>pyrepl_hacks</code></h2>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t install pyrepl-hacks <em>the usual way</em>.
Instead, I installed it in a very specific location.</p>

<p>I created a <code>~/.pyhacks</code> directory and then installed <code>pyrepl-hacks</code> <em>into</em> that directory:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ mkdir -p ~/.pyhacks
$ python -m pip install pyrepl-hacks --target ~/.pyhacks
</code></pre>

<p>In order for the <code>pyrepl_hacks</code> Python package to work, it needs to available within every Python REPL I might launch.
Normally that would mean that it needs to be installed in every virtual environment that Python runs within.
This trick avoids that constraint.</p>

<p>When Python tries to import a module, it iterates through the <code>sys.path</code> directory list.
Any Python packages found <em>within</em> any of the <code>sys.path</code> directories may be imported.</p>

<p>So monkey patching <code>sys.path</code> within my PYTHONSTARTUP file allows <code>pyrepl_hacks</code> to be imported in every Python interpreter I launch:</p>

<pre><code class="python">from pathlib import Path
import sys
sys.path.append(str(Path.home() / ".pyhacks"))
</code></pre>

<p>With those 3 lines (or something like them) placed in my PYTHONSTARTUP file, all interactive Python interpreters I launch will be able to import modules that are located in my <code>~/.pyhacks</code> directory.</p>

<h2>Creating your own custom REPL commands</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s pretty neat.
But what if you want to invent your own REPL commands?</p>

<p>Well, the <code>bind</code> utility I&rsquo;ve created in the <code>pyrepl_hacks</code> module can be used as a decorator for that.</p>

<p>This will make Ctrl+X followed by Ctrl+R insert <code>import subprocess</code> followed by <code>subprocess.run("", shell=True)</code> with the cursor positioned in between the double quotes after it&rsquo;s all inserted:</p>

<pre><code class="python">import pyrepl_hacks as _repl

@_repl.bind(r"Ctrl+X Ctrl+R", with_event=True)
def subprocess_run(reader, event_name, event):
    """Ctrl+X followed by Ctrl+R will insert a subprocess.run command."""
    reader.insert("import subprocess\n")
    code = 'subprocess.run("", shell=True)'
    reader.insert(code)
    for _ in range(len(code) - code.index('""') - 1):
        _repl.commands.left(reader, event_name, event)
</code></pre>

<p>You can read more about the ins and outs of the pyrepl-hacks package <a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/pyrepl-hacks#readme">in the readme file</a>.</p>

<h2>pyrepl-hacks is just a fancy wrapper</h2>

<p>The pyrepl-hacks package is really just a fancy wrapper around Python&rsquo;s <code>_pyrepl</code> and <code>_colorize</code> modules.</p>

<p>Why did I make a whole package and then modify my <code>sys.path</code> to use it, when I could have just used <code>_pyrepl</code> directly?</p>

<p>Three reasons:</p>

<ol>
<li>To make creating new commands <em>a bit</em> easier (functions can be used instead of classes)</li>
<li>To make the key bindings look a bit nicer (I prefer <code>"Ctrl+M"</code> over <code>r"\C-M"</code>)</li>
<li>To hide my hairy hacks behind a shiny API ✨</li>
</ol>


<p>Before I made pyrepl-hacks, I implemented these commands directly within my PYTHONSTARTUP file by reaching into the internals of <code>_pyrepl</code> directly.</p>

<p>My PYTHONSTARTUP file before pyrepl-hacks was <a href="https://pym.dev/p/35q9e/">over 100 lines longer</a>.</p>

<h2>Try pyrepl-hacks and leave feedback</h2>

<p>My hope is that the <a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/pyrepl-hacks">pyrepl-hacks</a> library will be obsolete one day.
Eventually the <code>_pyrepl</code> module might be renamed to <code>pyrepl</code> (or maybe just <code>repl</code>?) and it will have a well-documented friendly-ish public interface.</p>

<p>In the meantime, I plan to maintain pyrepl-hacks.
As Python 3.15 is developed, I&rsquo;ll make sure it continues to work.
And I may add more useful commands if I think of any.</p>

<p>If you hack your own REPL, I&rsquo;d love to hear what modifications you come up with.
And if you have thoughts on how to improve pyrepl-hacks, please open an issue or get in touch.</p>

<p>Also, <strong>if you use Windows</strong>, <a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/pyrepl-hacks/issues/1">please help me</a> confirm <strong>whether certain keys work on Windows</strong>. Thanks!</p>

<p>Contributions and ideas welcome!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Customizing your Python REPL's color scheme (Python 3.14+)]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2025/09/customizing-your-python-repl-color-scheme/"/>
    <updated>2025-09-04T14:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2025/09/customizing-your-python-repl-color-scheme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Did you know that Python 3.14 will include <a href="https://docs.python.org/3.14/whatsnew/3.14.html#whatsnew314-pyrepl-highlighting">syntax highlighting</a> in the REPL?</p>

<p>Python 3.14 is due to be <a href="https://peps.python.org/pep-0745/">officially released</a> in about a month.
I recommended tweaking your Python setup now so you&rsquo;ll have your ideal color scheme on release day.</p>

<p><img src="/images/python3.14-repl-syntax-highlighting.png" title="Python 3.14 REPL with syntax highlighting using custom color scheme" ></p>

<p>But&hellip; what if the default syntax colors don&rsquo;t match the colors that your text editor uses?</p>

<p>Well, fortunately you can customize your color scheme!</p>

<p><strong>Warning</strong>: I am recommending using an undocumented private module (it has an <code>_</code>-prefixed name) which may change in future Python versions.
Do not use this module in production code.</p>

<h2>Installing Python 3.14</h2>

<p>Don&rsquo;t have Python 3.14 installed yet?</p>

<p>If you have <a href="https://docs.astral.sh/uv/">uv</a> installed, you can run this command to launch Python 3.14:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ uv run --python 3.14 python
</code></pre>

<p>That will automatically install 3.14 (if you don&rsquo;t have it yet) and run it.</p>

<h2>Setting a theme</h2>

<p>I have my terminal colors set to the Solarized Light color palette and I have Vim use a Solarized Light color scheme as well.</p>

<p>The REPL doesn&rsquo;t <em>quite</em> match my text editor by default:</p>

<p><img src="/images/python3.14-repl-default-color-scheme.png" title="Python 3.14 REPL with default syntax highlighting" ></p>

<p>The numbers, comments, strings, and keywords are all different colors than my text editor.</p>

<p>This code makes the Python REPL use <em>nearly</em> the same syntax highlighting as my text editor:</p>

<pre><code class="python">from _colorize import set_theme, default_theme, Syntax, ANSIColors

set_theme(default_theme.copy_with(
    syntax=Syntax(
        keyword=ANSIColors.GREEN,
        builtin=ANSIColors.BLUE,
        comment=ANSIColors.INTENSE_BLUE,
        string=ANSIColors.CYAN,
        number=ANSIColors.CYAN,
        definition=ANSIColors.BLUE,
        soft_keyword=ANSIColors.BOLD_GREEN,
        op=ANSIColors.INTENSE_GREEN,
        reset=ANSIColors.RESET + ANSIColors.INTENSE_GREEN,
    ),
))
</code></pre>

<p>Check it out:</p>

<p><img src="/images/python3.14-repl-syntax-highlighting.png" title="Python 3.14 REPL with syntax highlighting using custom color scheme" ></p>

<p>Neat, right?</p>

<p>But&hellip; I want this to be enabled by default!</p>

<h2>Using a <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> file</h2>

<p>You can use a <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> file to run code every time a new Python process starts.</p>

<p>If Python sees a <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> environment variable when it starts up, it will open that file and evaluate the code within it.</p>

<p>I have this in my <code>~/.zshrc</code> file to set the <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> environment variable to <code>~/.startup.py</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="bash"># Setup python-launcher to use startup file
export PYTHONSTARTUP=$HOME/.startup.py
</code></pre>

<p>In my <code>~/.startup.py</code> file, I have this code:</p>

<pre><code class="python">def _main():
    """Everything's in a function to avoid polluting the global scope."""
    try:
        from _colorize import set_theme, default_theme, Syntax, ANSIColors
    except ImportError:
        pass  # Python 3.13 and below
    else:
        # Define Solarized Light colors
        solarized_light_theme = default_theme.copy_with(
            syntax=Syntax(
                keyword=ANSIColors.GREEN,
                builtin=ANSIColors.BLUE,
                comment=ANSIColors.INTENSE_BLUE,
                string=ANSIColors.CYAN,
                number=ANSIColors.CYAN,
                definition=ANSIColors.BLUE,
                soft_keyword=ANSIColors.BOLD_GREEN,
                op=ANSIColors.INTENSE_GREEN,
                reset=ANSIColors.RESET + ANSIColors.INTENSE_GREEN,
            ),
        )
        set_theme(solarized_light_theme)

_main()  # _main avoids name collision, in case python -i is used
del _main  # Delete _main from global scope
</code></pre>

<p>Note that:</p>

<ol>
<li>I put all relevant code within a <code>_main</code> function so that the variables I set don&rsquo;t remain in the global scope of the Python REPL (they will by default)</li>
<li>I call the <code>_main</code> function and then delete the function afterward, again so the <code>_main</code> variable doesn&rsquo;t stay floating around in my REPL</li>
<li>I use <code>try</code>-<code>except</code>-<code>else</code> to ensure errors don&rsquo;t occur on Python 3.13 and below</li>
</ol>


<p>Also note that the syntax highlighting in the new REPL is <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/issues/134953">not as fine-grained</a> as many other syntax highlighting tools.
I suspect that it may become a bit more granular over time, <strong>which may break the above code</strong>.</p>

<p>The <code>_colorize</code> module is currently an internal implementation detail and is deliberately undocumented.
Its API may change at any time, so <strong>the above code may break in Python 3.15</strong>.
If that happens, I&rsquo;ll just update my <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> file at that point.</p>

<h2>Packaging themes</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve stuck all of the above code in a <code>~/.startup.py</code> file and I set the <code>PYTHONSTARTUP</code> environment variable on my system to point to this file.</p>

<p>Instead of manually updating a startup file, is there any way to make these themes <em>installable</em>?</p>

<p>Well, if a <code>.pth</code> file is included in Python&rsquo;s <code>site-packages</code> directory, that file (which must be a single line) will be run whenever Python starts up.
In theory, a package could use such a file to import a module and then call a function that would set the color scheme for the REPL.
My <a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/dramatic">dramatic</a> package uses (<em>cough</em> abuses <em>cough</em>) <code>.pth</code> files in this way.</p>

<p>This sounds like a somewhat bad idea, but maybe not a <em>horrible</em> idea.</p>

<p>If you do this, let me know.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s your theme?</h2>

<p>Have you played with setting a theme in your own Python REPL?</p>

<p>What theme are you using?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My PyCon US 2025 recap]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2025/06/pycon-us-2025-recap/"/>
    <updated>2025-06-11T16:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2025/06/pycon-us-2025-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m pretty much fully back to normal life after PyCon US 2025.</p>

<p>I started writing this post shortly after PyCon, got side-tracked, and now I&rsquo;m finally publishing it.</p>

<p><strong>My very quick recap</strong>: I spent a ton of time at PyCon chatting with folks and I <em>really</em> enjoyed it.
As Ned wrote, <a href="https://nedbatchelder.com/blog/202505/pycon_summer_camp.html">it&rsquo;s like summer camp</a>.</p>

<h2>My pre-conference (Monday and Tuesday)</h2>

<p>I flew in a couple days early (Monday May 12) because Breeze airlines had a non-stop flight from San Diego to Pittsburgh that only ran on Monday or Friday.
I listened to <a href="http://robertdputnam.com/the-upswing/">The Upswing</a> as I flew in and wondered <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114496799621377766">how we can make our community less individualistic</a>.</p>

<p>On Tuesday, I went on <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114495825740774796">a walking tour</a> of downtown Pittsburgh.
Then I ate Indian food for lunch at Sree&rsquo;s, which I chose because I saw they had great vegan lunch options and weren&rsquo;t open for dinner.
I was eating vegan during PyCon US (as I <em>mostly</em> do at home) and I remembered to do <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114506541091205849">some research on vegan dinner restaurants in the area</a> this year.</p>

<p>On Tuesday night, as CPython core devs started showing up in the Westin lobby, I went on a walk with Anthony Shaw.
Anthony asked whether I was up for &ldquo;an adventure&rdquo; and I said yes without asking questions.
We walked across the river to Randyland (a.k.a. &ldquo;the mattress factory&rdquo;).
It was fun, interesting, and quite odd.
We were the only ones there and had plenty of time to look around at all the interesting items and art pieces that Randy had collected.</p>

<p>Anthony and I did dinner at Condado&rsquo;s and ran into more conference friends at the bar (Kattni, Rose, and Kojo).</p>

<h2>My tutorial on decorators (Wednesday)</h2>

<p>Wednesday was my tutorial day.</p>

<p>Attendees used sticky notes during the exercise sections to note when they needed help.
I wrote about this system in my <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2025/05/how-to-give-a-great-pycon-tutorial/">blog post of tips for giving a good PyCon tutorial</a>.</p>

<p>The tutorial went well and the attendees seemed to enjoy it.</p>

<h2>The newcomer&rsquo;s orientation &amp; education summit (Thursday)</h2>

<p>Just before the opening reception on Thursday evening, Kojo, Sumana, and I ran the <a href="https://mastodon.social/@pycon@fosstodon.org/114512798321665686">newcomer&rsquo;s orientation</a>.
Figuring out what exactly we want to say to help orient folks to PyCon is always a bit challenging.
A first-time PyCon attendee gave me some ideas for how we could do it even better next year.
I&rsquo;ve taken notes and will revisit them later.</p>

<p>I also attended a few talks during education summit earlier in the day.
Reuven Lerner gave a talk on how he recommends his students use LLMs and I was pleased to hear many suggestions that are closely aligned with what I recommend as well as a few insights I hadn&rsquo;t heard before.</p>

<h2>My lightning talk (Friday)</h2>

<p>I gave a lightning talk on Friday evening (the first talk day).
I called it <a href="https://youtu.be/Uuhu-F05A7k?feature=shared&amp;t=3174">Systems, gates, and rage</a>.
It seemed to go over well.
Folks occasionally told me throughout the conference that they enjoyed it.
I won&rsquo;t spoil the topic of my lightning talk (you&rsquo;ll need to watch it) but it&rsquo;s a topic that I&rsquo;d been thinking about for a few months.</p>

<p>Rodrigo gave a <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114519939925398070">meta lightning talk</a> as the first talk of the first day.
I gave a meta lightning talk last year in the same slot.
I hope this becomes a tradition, where the first lightning talk is a talk about someone explaining how to give a lightning talk.</p>

<h2>The keynotes</h2>

<p>I really enjoyed the keynotes this year.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/ydVmzg_SJLw?feature=shared">Cory Doctorow&rsquo;s opening keynote</a> was <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114519939925398070"><em>really</em> thought-provoking</a> and <a href="https://youtu.be/Bglsof9b23k?feature=shared">Lynn Root&rsquo;s keynote</a> was on the importance <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114519939925398070">of &ldquo;play&rdquo;</a>, which is a topic I&rsquo;ve written about before to my <a href="https://pym.dev/newsletter">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/qog-dGVhSBI?feature=shared">The Marshall project</a> keynote and <a href="https://youtu.be/3UOLpTA7pRI?feature=shared">The Carpentries</a> keynote were also great, though I missed portions of each (beginning of one and end of another) and ended up watching the full videos online after the conference.</p>

<h2>The hallway track</h2>

<p>The &ldquo;hallway track&rdquo; is the way many PyCon attendees describe <strong>the discussions that happen organically in the hallway</strong>.</p>

<p>These discussions can happen at any time, including breaks, breakfast, lunch, and even during talks. I missed at least 3 talks this year because I was having a great discussion in the hallway and time got away from me.</p>

<p>PyCon&rsquo;s venue in Pittsburgh included a great <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114512971414412295">rooftop</a> so the <strong>rooftop track</strong> / <strong>garden track</strong> was a lovely spin in the hallway track this year.</p>

<h2>The open spaces</h2>

<p>The open spaces are a very important part of PyCon for me.</p>

<p>Like the hallway track, the open spaces are mostly (usually) about having a conversation.
Unlike the hallway track, the open spaces have a <strong>set topic</strong>.</p>

<p>I attended open spaces (and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114526876252905533">ran my own</a>):</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Education and Outreach Working Group Open Space</strong>: I&rsquo;m part of this newly revived work group and we held this to hear topics that community members are interested in seeing the PSF focus on more deliberately</li>
<li><strong>t-strings: Let&rsquo;s build powerful templating together</strong>: I am interested in the new t-string feature in Python 3.14 and wanted to listen to this conversation (I contributed <em>a little bit</em> too)</li>
<li><strong>Computer Assisted Reporting and Investigative journalism</strong>: I was curious to hear this conversation, which included journalists, government employees who respond to information requests, and many others</li>
<li><strong>Python Skill-Building</strong>: I ran this open space on the roof during lunch time to chat about different Python skill-building services, including my own (<a href="https://pym.dev">Python Morsels</a>)</li>
<li><strong>Ask a Friendly Meat-Loving Vegan</strong>: I also ran this open space, inspired by a conversation I had the night before in a hotel lobby about animal farming, veganism, nutrition, and other related topics I&rsquo;ve thought/read a lot about</li>
</ul>


<p>I enjoyed meeting folks with similar interests and having fun and productive conversations (or at least listening to interesting conversations) in those open spaces.</p>

<h2>Dinners, games, and hotel lobby conversations</h2>

<p>I ate at Bae Bae&rsquo;s, Rosewater Grill, and APTEKA during the conference.
I also ate at Condado&rsquo;s at least 3 nights.</p>

<p>APTEKA was a fun trek for <a href="https://mastodon.social/@pythonbynight@fosstodon.org/114525581821316666">vegan PierogiCon</a> with mostly non-vegan folks.
I&rsquo;m sure the pierogis weren&rsquo;t authentic, but we all loved the food.</p>

<p>After dinner every night I went to the Westin lobby and either played <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2015/06/cabo-card-game/">the Cabo card game</a> or chatted with folks (<a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114509076754402356">1</a>, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114514682814457694">2</a>, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/114525878624139679">3</a>).</p>

<h2>On missing talks</h2>

<p>The keynotes and lightning talks are usually my favorite parts of PyCon.
I tried to watch as many live keynotes and lightning talk sessions as I could this year.
The morning lightning talks were hard to make it to because I kept sleeping in late enough that I missed most of them.</p>

<p>Ultimately, I watched <em>very few</em> live talks.
I missed talks due to sleeping in, attending open spaces, visiting booths in the exhibit hall, getting lost in conversations in the hallway, and mid-day taking naps (in my hotel room, not during talks!).</p>

<p>Hynek has <a href="https://hynek.me/articles/hallway-track/">written about the downside of the hallway track and the importance of attending talks</a>.
I sympathize with Hynek&rsquo;s argument that the hallway track is a trade off and there are downsides to missing talks, for both attendees and speakers.
I am grateful that folks give talks and I want to support folks who do give talks, and yet, I often find myself attending few talks.</p>

<p>Ironically, the one talk I ended up taking a nap through (again, in my hotel room, not <em>in the talk</em>) was Hynek&rsquo;s.
My brain was fried by the time of his talk and I&rsquo;m glad I was able to watch it online the week after PyCon.
He apparently had a completely packed room as it was!</p>

<p>I did make sure to show up to a talk by a conference friend who I wanted to support (Michael Dahlberg&rsquo;s <a href="https://youtu.be/LseCKvrp6og?feature=shared">talk on honeybee swarms</a>).
I have also binge-watched a dozen or so talks online that I had planned to attend but missed during PyCon.</p>

<p>You can <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@PyConUS/videos">watch all talks online now</a> (at least I <em>think</em> they&rsquo;re all up now?).</p>

<h2>Attend a Python event</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m looking forward to PyCon coming to Long Beach next year.
I&rsquo;m in San Diego and it will be nice to <em>not fly</em> to a PyCon for once!</p>

<p>I highly recommend attending local Python meetups, attending regional Python conferences, and/or attending PyCon US.
Most in-person Python community events are <em>pretty lovely</em>.
The Python community generally goes out of its way to be more welcoming than most tech events.</p>

<p>See you in Long Beach!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
