<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: editorconfig | Trey Hunner]]></title>
  <link href="https://treyhunner.com/blog/categories/editorconfig/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://treyhunner.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-11-19T15:44:38-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://treyhunner.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Trey Hunner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maintaining consistent coding conventions with EditorConfig]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2012/02/editorconfig/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-17T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2012/02/editorconfig</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I often have indentation issues when coding because I work with many open
source (and closed source) projects that have different identation styles.  For
example, my <a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/jquery-formrestrict">jQuery formrestrict</a> uses 4 spaces for indentation,
<a href="https://github.com/kswedberg/jquery-expander">jQuery expander</a> uses 2 spaces, and <a href="https://github.com/gbirke/jquery_pagination">jQuery pagination</a> uses hard tabs.
I don&rsquo;t want to change my text editor&rsquo;s indentation settings every time I open
one of these files and using a plugin to auto-detect indentation is only a
partial solution.  To solve this problem I started a project I call
EditorConfig.</p>

<p><a href="http://editorconfig.org">EditorConfig</a> defines coding conventions for groups of files and instructs
text editors to adhere to these conventions.  To solve my problem, I just
create a file called <code>.editorconfig</code> that sets indentation for my files and
with my EditorConfig plugin installed Vim takes care of the rest.  Here&rsquo;s an
example <code>.editorconfig</code> file I could add to my project that uses
<a href="https://github.com/kswedberg/jquery-expander">jQuery expander</a> and <a href="https://github.com/gbirke/jquery_pagination">jQuery pagination</a>:</p>

<pre><code class="ini .editorconfig">    [*.js]
    indent_style = space
    indent_size = 4

    [jquery.expander.js]
    indent_style = space
    indent_size = 2

    [jquery.pagination.js]
    indent_style = tab
    indent_size = 4
</code></pre>

<p>With this <code>.editorconfig</code> file, all JavaScript files use 4 spaces for
indentation except for <code>jquery.expander.js</code> which uses 2 spaces and
<code>jquery.pagination.js</code> which uses hard tabs with a column width of 4.  If I put
my <code>.editorconfig</code> file under version control, other developers working on my
project can see the coding conventions I defined and if their text editor has
an EditorConfig plugin installed their editor will automatically use the
correct indentation as well.</p>

<p>Example EditorConfig files can be seen in my own projects (such as
<a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/dotfiles/blob/master/.editorconfig">in my dotfiles repo</a>) and in the
<a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/dotfiles/blob/master/.editorconfig">various EditorConfig plugin codebases</a>.  More
information on EditorConfig can be found at the
<a href="http://editorconfig.org">EditorConfig website</a>.</p>

<p>EditorConfig plugins are <a href="http://editorconfig.org/#download">available for 6 different editors</a>
now.  If you like the idea, <a href="http://editorconfig.org">try out EditorConfig</a> for your
favorite editor and <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/editorconfig">tell us what you think</a>.  If you don&rsquo;t like
the idea or have a problem with EditorConfig please <a href="https://github.com/editorconfig/editorconfig/issues">submit an issue</a>,
add a thread to <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/editorconfig">the mailing list</a>, or send me an email voicing
your concern.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
