<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pycon | Trey Hunner]]></title>
  <link href="https://treyhunner.com/blog/categories/pycon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://treyhunner.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-01-22T14:29:34-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://treyhunner.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Trey Hunner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PyCon 2024 Reflection]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2024/05/pycon-2024-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2024-05-28T13:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2024/05/pycon-2024-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I traveled back home from PyCon US 2024 last week.
This is my reflection on my time at PyCon.</p>

<h2>Attempting to eat vegan</h2>

<p>Since 2020, I&rsquo;ve been <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/111794737871397453">gradually eating more plant-based</a> and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/111982459215543497">a few months ago</a> I decided to take PyCon as an opportunity to attempt exclusively vegan eating outside my own home.
As <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/112493037289419028">I noted on Mastodon</a>, it was a challenge and I failed every day at least once but I found the experience worthwhile.
Our food system is <em>very</em> dairy-oriented.</p>

<h2>Staying hydrated and fed</h2>

<p>One of the first things I did before heading to the convention center was walk to Target and buy snacks and drinks.
When at PyCon, I prefer to spend 30 minutes and $20 to have a backup plan for last minute hydration and calories (even if not the <em>greatest</em> calories).
I never quite know when I might sleep through breakfast, find lunch lacking, or wish I&rsquo;d eaten more dinner.</p>

<h2>A tutorial, an orientation, a lightning talk, and open spaces</h2>

<p>My responsibilities at PyCon this year included teaching a tutorial and helping run the Newcomer&rsquo;s Orientation with <a href="https://x.com/KojoIdrissa">Kojo</a> and <a href="https://social.coop/@brainwane">Sumana</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/112479031063220835">Yngve and Marie</a> offered to act as teaching assistants during my tutorial and I was very grateful for their help!
<a href="https://x.com/mathsppblog">Rodrigo</a> and Krishna also offered to TA just before my tutorial started and I was extra grateful to have even more help than I&rsquo;d expected.
The attendees were mostly better prepared than I expected they would be, which was also great.
It&rsquo;s always great to spend less time on setup and more time exploring Python together.</p>

<p>The newcomer&rsquo;s orientation the next day went well.
We kept it fairly brief and were able to address about 10 minutes of audience questions before the opening reception started.</p>

<p>Once my PyCon responsibilities completed, I invented a few more (light) responsibilities for myself. 😅
I signed up to give a lightning talk on how to give a lightning talk.
They slotted it as the first talk of the first lightning talk session on Friday night.
I kept this talk pretty much the same as the one <a href="https://youtu.be/aNHBr7q-KVw?feature=shared&amp;t=915">I presented DjangoCon 2016</a>.
I could have made the transitions fancier, but I decided to embrace the idea of simplicity with the hope that audience members might think &ldquo;look if that first speaker can give such a simple and succinct presentation, maybe I can too.&rdquo;</p>

<p>On Saturday I ran <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/112457077109815019">an open space on Python Learning</a>.
Some of you showed up because you&rsquo;re on my mailing list or you&rsquo;re paying Python Morsels subscribers.
Many folks showed up because the topic was interesting, either as a learner or as a teacher.
I really enjoyed the round-table-style conversation we had.</p>

<p>I also ran a <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/112468136603503893">Cabo Card game open space</a> during lunch on Sunday on the 4th floor rooftop.
Cabo is my usual conference ice breaker game and I played it at least a few nights <a href="https://mas.to/@davidism/112465501797531611">in The Westin lobby</a> as well.</p>

<h2>Seeing conference friends, old and new</h2>

<p>For me, PyCon is largely about having conversations.
The talks and tutorials are great for starting me thinking about an idea.
The hallway track, open spaces, and meals are great for continuing conversations about those ideas (or <em>other</em> ideas).</p>

<p>My first morning in Pittsburgh, I chatted with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/naomiceder/">Naomi</a> and <a href="https://x.com/reuvenmlerner/">Reuven</a>.
I&rsquo;m glad I ran into them before the conference kicked off because (as often happens at PyCon) I only very briefly saw either of them during the rest of PyCon!</p>

<p>After my tutorial that afternoon, I did dinner with Marie, Yngve, and Rodrigo at Rosewater Mediterranean (good vegan options, assuming you enjoy falafel and various sauces).
As sometimes happens at PyCon, another PyCon attendee, Sachin, joined our table because we noticed him eating on his own at a table near us and invited him to join us.</p>

<p>On Saturday, <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@melaniearbor">Melanie</a>, <a href="https://mas.to/@davidism">David</a>, <a href="https://x.com/kjaymiller">Jay</a>, and I had a sort of mini San Diego Python study group reunion dinner before inviting folks to join us for <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/112465503888730383">Cabo and Knucklebones</a> one night.
The 4 of us originally met each other (along with <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@willingc">Carol</a> and other wonderful Python folks) at the San Diego Python study group about 10 years ago.</p>

<p>I had some wonderful conversations about ways to improve the Python documentation over dinner (at Nicky&rsquo;s Thai) on Sunday night with <em>so</em> many docs-concerned folks who I highly respect.
I&rsquo;m really excited that Python has <a href="https://peps.python.org/pep-0732/">the documentation editorial board</a> and I&rsquo;m hopeful that that board, with the help of many others community members, will usher in big improvements to the documentation in the coming years.</p>

<p>I also met a number of Internet acquaintances IRL for the first time at PyCon.
I met <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tereza-iofciu/">Tereza</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jessica0greene/">Jessica</a>, who I know from our work in the PSF Code of Conduct workgroup.
I met <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@slott56">Steve Lott</a>, who I originally knew as <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/users/10661/s-lott">a prolific question-answerer</a>.
I also met <a href="https://github.com/hugovk">Hugo</a>, a CPython core dev, the Python 3.14 &amp; 3.15 release manager, and a <a href="https://mastodon.social/@hugovk">social media user</a> (which is how I&rsquo;ve primarily interacted with him because the Internet is occasionally lovely).
I was also very excited to meet many <a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com">Python Morsels members</a> as well as folks who know me through <a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/newsletter/">my weekly Python tips newsletter</a>.</p>

<p>I was grateful to chat with <a href="https://mastodon.social/@hynek">Hynek</a> and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@AlSweigart">Al</a> about creating talks, YouTube videos, and other online content.
I also enjoyed chatting with <a href="https://mastodon.social/@glyph">Glyph</a> a bit about our experiences consulting and training and (in hindsight) wished I&rsquo;d planned an open space for either consultants or trainers, both of which have been held at PyCon before but it just takes someone to stick it on the open space board.</p>

<p>Many folks I only saw very briefly (I said a quick hi and bye to <a href="https://aeracode.org/@andrew">Andrew</a> over lunch during the sprints) and some I didn&rsquo;t see at all (<a href="https://mastodon.social/@frank@frankwiles.social">Frank</a> was at PyCon but we never ran into each other).
Some I essentially saw through playing a few rounds of Cabo (<a href="https://social.coop/@Yhg1s">Thomas</a> and <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@ethantyping">Ethan</a> among many others).
We also ran into at least 4 other PyCon attendees in the airport on Tuesday afternoon, including <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/bbelderbos/">Bob</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/juliansequeira/">Julian</a>, who it&rsquo;s always a pleasure to see.</p>

<h2>A Mastodon-oriented PyCon</h2>

<p>On Thursday night I had the feeling that the number of Mastodon posts I saw on the <strong>#PyConUS</strong> hashtag was greater than the number of Twitter posts.
I (very unscientifically) counted up the number of posts I was seeing on each and found that my perception was correct: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/112453920848761679">Mastodon seemed to slightly overtake Twitter at PyCon this year</a>.</p>

<p>Over dinner on Wednesday, I tried to convince Marie, Yngve, and Rodrigo to get Mastodon accounts just to follow the hashtag during PyCon.
I succeeded: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/112479031063220835">Marie and Yngve</a> and <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@davep/112458736212760528">Rodrigo</a>!</p>

<p>Mastodon will never be <em>the</em> social media platform.
Its decentralized nature is too much of a barrier for many folks.
However, it does seem to be used by <em>enough</em> somewhat nerdy Python folks to now be one the most used social media platform for PyCon posting.</p>

<h2>The talks</h2>

<p>I ended up spending little time in the talks during PyCon.
This wasn&rsquo;t on purpose.
I just happened to attend many open spaces, take personal breaks, and end up in hallway conversations often.
I did see many of the lightning talks live, as well as <a href="https://x.com/kjaymiller">Jay</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/@simon">Simon</a>, and <a href="https://social.coop/@brainwane">Sumana</a>&rsquo;s keynotes (all of them were exceptional) and the opening and closing remarks.
I also watched a few talks from my hotel room while taking breaks.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;m often a bit light on my talk load at PyCon, I do recommend folks attend a good handful of live talks during PyCon, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@jonafato/112514979873634457">as Jon</a> and <a href="https://hynek.me/articles/hallway-track/">others</a> recommend.
I wish I had seen more talks live.
I also wish I had attended a few open spaces that I missed.</p>

<p>At any one time, I know that I&rsquo;m always missing about 90% of what&rsquo;s scheduled during PyCon (if you include the talks <em>and</em> the open spaces).
That&rsquo;s assuming I don&rsquo;t ditch the conference entirely for a few hours and <a href="https://social.coop/@bitprophet/112452662184950234">walk across a bridge</a> or <a href="https://mastodon.social/@AlSweigart/112514009252817862">ride a funicular</a> (neither of which I did, as I stuck around the venue the whole time this year).
I am glad I saw, did, and talked about everything I did, but there&rsquo;s always something I wish I&rsquo;d seen/done!</p>

<h2>The sprints</h2>

<p>Thanks to the documentation dinner, I had a couple documentation-related ideas in mind on the first day of sprints.
But I&rsquo;m also <em>really</em> excited about the new Python REPL coming in Python 3.13 (<a href="https://x.com/treyhunner/status/1720185049461801371">in case</a> you <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2024/05/installing-a-custom-python-build-with-pyenv/">can&rsquo;t tell</a> from <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2024/05/my-favorite-python-3-dot-13-feature/">how much</a> I <a href="https://x.com/treyhunner/status/1788307498715554160">talk</a> about <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/treyhunner_python-activity-7194082747315859456-qQjk/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">it</a>), so I sprinted on that instead.
<a href="https://github.com/ambv">Łukasz</a> assigned me the task of researching keyboard shortcuts that the new REPL is missing (compared to the current one on Linux and Mac) so <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/issues/119034#issuecomment-2121142576">I spent some time researching that</a>.
I got to see the REPL running on <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@tonybaloney/112477098396842900">Anthony&rsquo;s laptop</a> on Windows and I am <em>so excited</em> that Windows support will be included before 3.13.0 lands! 🎉</p>

<p>Partly inspired by <a href="https://youtu.be/RL3HFj5SDqI?t=1549">Carol Willing&rsquo;s PyCon preview message</a>, I also thanked <a href="https://github.com/pablogsal">Pablo</a>, <a href="https://github.com/ambv">Łukasz</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/lysnikolaou">Lysandros</a> in-person for all their work on the new Python REPL. 🤗</p>

<h2>Until next year</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be <a href="https://www.pyohio.org/2024/program/speakers/keynote-speakers/#trey-hunner">keynoting at PyOhio</a> this year.</p>

<p>Besides PyOhio, I&rsquo;m not sure whether I&rsquo;ll make it to another conference until PyCon US next year.
I&rsquo;d love to attend all of them, but I do have work and personal goals that need accomplishing too!</p>

<p>I hope to see you at PyCon US 2025!
In the meantime, if you&rsquo;re wishing we&rsquo;d exchanged contact details or met in-person, please feel free to stay in touch through <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner">Mastodon</a>, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://pym.dev/newsletter">my weekly emails</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@PythonMorsels">YouTube</a>, or <a href="http://twitter.com/treyhunner">Twitter</a>.</p>

<p><img class="&ldquo;no-border&rdquo;" src="/images/pycon2024-pic.jpg" title="&ldquo;&rdquo; &ldquo;Yellow bridges over a river just outside the PyCon 2024 conference center in Pittsburgh&rdquo;" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10 years of Python conferences]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2024/04/10-years-of-python-conferences/"/>
    <updated>2024-04-27T11:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2024/04/10-years-of-python-conferences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>10 years and 10 days ago I flew home from my very first Python conference.</p>

<p>I left a few days into the PyCon US 2014 sprints and I remember feeling a bit like summer camp was ending.
I&rsquo;d played board games, contributed to an open source project, seen tons of talks, and met a <em>ton</em> of people.</p>

<h2>My first Python conference: PyCon US 2014</h2>

<p>PyCon 2014 was the first Python conference I attended.</p>

<p>At the start of the conference I only knew a handful of San Diegans.
I left having met many more folks.
Some of the folks I met I knew from online forums, GitHub repos, or videos
I met Kenneth Love, Baptiste Mispelon, Carl Meyer, Eric Holscher in-person, among many others.
Most folks I met I had never encountered online, but I was glad to have met in person.</p>

<p>For the most part, I had no idea who anyone was, what they did with Python, or what they might be interested in talking about.
I also had no idea what most of the various non-talk activities were.
I found out about the Education Summit and hadn&rsquo;t realized that it required pre-registration.
The open spaces are one of my favorite parts of PyCon and I didn&rsquo;t even they existed until PyCon 2015.</p>

<p>I <em>did</em> stay for a couple days of the sprints and I was grateful for that.
Most of the memorable human connections I had were during the sprints.
I helped <a href="https://pyvideo.org">PyVideo</a> upgrade their code base from Python 2 to Python 3 (this was before Will and Sheila <a href="https://pyvideo.org/pages/thanks-will-and-sheila.html">stepped down as maintainers</a>).
Will guided me through the code base and seemed grateful for the help.</p>

<p>I also got the idea to write front-end JavaScript tests for Django during the sprints and eventually <a href="https://github.com/django/deps/blob/main/final/0003-javascript-tests.rst">started that process</a> after PyCon thanks to Carl Meyer&rsquo;s guidance.</p>

<h2>Attending regional conferences and DjangoCon</h2>

<p>In fall 2014, I attended Django BarCamp at the Eventbrite office.
That was my first exposure to the idea of an &ldquo;unconference&rdquo;&hellip; which I kept in mind when I spotted the open spaces board at PyCon 2015.</p>

<p>Before coming back to Montreal for <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/585969805796212736">PyCon 2015</a>, I emailed Harry Percival to ask if he could use a teaching assistant during his tutorial on writing tests. His reply was much more enthusiastic than I expected: &ldquo;YES YES OH GOD YES THANK YOU THANK YOU THANK YOU TREY&rdquo;.
I was very honored to be able to help Harry, as my testing workflow was <em>heavily</em> inspired by many blog posts he&rsquo;d written about testing best practices in Django.</p>

<p>I coached at my first Django Girls event in 2015 in Ensenada and then my second at <a href="https://twitter.com/algosuna/status/641421944005378048">DjangoCon 2015</a> in Austin. I gave my first lightning talk at DjangoCon 2015, comparing modern JavaScript to Python. It was a lightning talk I had given at the San Diego JavaScript and <a href="https://www.sandiegopython.org">San Diego Python</a> meetups.</p>

<p>In 2016, I attended PyTennessee in Nashville. I remember attending a dinner of of about a dozen folks who spoke at the conference. I was grateful to get to chat with so many folks whose talks I&rsquo;d attended.</p>

<h2>Presenting talks and tutorials</h2>

<p>I presented my first conference tutorial at <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/737069721292439552">PyCon 2016</a> in Portland and <a href="https://pyvideo.org/djangocon-us-2016/readability-counts.html">my first talk</a> at <a href="https://twitter.com/asendecka/status/756851845012844544">DjangoCon US 2016</a> in Philadelphia.
I had been presenting lightning talks every few months at my local Python and JavaScript meetups for a few years by then and I had hosted free workshops at my local meetup and paid workshops for training clients.</p>

<p>Having presented locally helped, but presenting on a big stage is always scary.</p>

<h2>Volunteering</h2>

<p>I volunteered at some of my first few conferences and found that I really enjoyed it.
I especially enjoyed running the registration desk, as you&rsquo;re often the first helpful face that people see coming into the conference.</p>

<p>During PyCon 2016, 2017, and 2018, I co-chaired the open spaces thanks to Anna Ossowski inviting me to help.
I had first attended open spaces during PyCon 2015 and I <em>loved</em> them.
Talks are great, but so are discussions!</p>

<p>I also ran for the PSF board of directors in 2016 and ended up serving on the board for a few years before stepping down.
After my board terms, I volunteered for the PSF Code of Conduct working group for about 6 years.
I didn&rsquo;t even know what the PSF <em>was</em> until PyCon 2015!</p>

<h2>A <em>lot</em> of travel&hellip; maybe too much</h2>

<p>After DjangoCon 2016, I went a bit conference-wild.
I attended <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/829412120370565120">PyTennessee 2017</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/PythonChat/status/845052805375295488">PyCaribbean 2017</a> in Puerto Rico, <a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/866382369619562496">PyCon US 2017</a> in Portland, <a href="https://twitter.com/asteracode/status/893274761727361024">PyCon Australia 2017</a> in Melbourne, <a href="https://twitter.com/TobiasMcNulty/status/896570680933703681">DjangoCon 2017</a> in Spokane, <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/916890505157468160">PyGotham 2017</a> in NYC, and <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/937441419966296064">North Bay Python 2017</a> in Petaluma.</p>

<p>In 2018 I sponsored <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/962862235734495232">PyTennessee</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/jmwatt3/status/1023713820752183296">PyOhio</a> and spoke at both.
I passed out chocolate chip cookies at PyTennessee as a way to announce the launch of <a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com">Python Morsels</a>.
I also attended <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/996881842820272128">PyCon 2018</a> in Cleveland, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/144080672@N05/31764542868/">DjangoCon 2018</a> in San Diego, <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/1048340952451047425">PyGotham 2018</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/nnja/status/1058589935618318336">North Bay Python 2018</a>.</p>

<p>I slowed down <em>a bit</em> in 2019, with just <a href="https://twitter.com/LaylaSells_cshs/status/1100058649227972609">PyCascades</a> (Seattle), <a href="https://twitter.com/mariatta/status/1125534406851084288">PyCon US</a> (Cleveland), <a href="https://twitter.com/juliansequeira/status/1157106403598749698">PyCon Australia</a> (Sydney), and DjangoCon US (San Diego, which is home for me).</p>

<h2>Since the pandemic</h2>

<p>Since the start of the pandemic, I&rsquo;ve attended <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/1519724687890128899">PyCon US 2022</a>, DjangoCon 2022 in San Diego (in my city for the <em>third</em> time!) and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@treyhunner/110243968672457367">PyCon US 2023</a>.
Traveling is more challenging for me than it used to be, but I hope to attend more regional conferences again soon.</p>

<p>Between client work, I&rsquo;ve been focusing less on conferences and more on blog posts (<a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/articles/">over here</a>), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@PythonMorsels">screencasts</a>, my <a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/newsletter/">weekly Python tips</a> emails, and (of course) on <a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com">Python Morsels</a>.</p>

<h2>My journey started locally</h2>

<p>I became part of the Python community before I knew I was part of it.</p>

<p>I started using Python professionally in December 2009 and I attended my first San Diego Python meetup in March 2012.
I met the organizers, gave some lightning talks, attended Saturday study group sessions (thanks Carol Willing, Alain Domissy, and others for running these), and volunteered to help organize meetups, study groups, and workshops.</p>

<p>By 2014, I had learned from folks online and in-person and I had helped out at my local Python meetup.
I had even made a few contributions to some small Django packages I relied on heavily.</p>

<p>I was encouraged to attend PyCon 2014 by others who were attending (thanks Carol, Micah, and Paul among others).
The conference was well-worth the occasional feeling of overwhelm.</p>

<h2>We&rsquo;re all just people</h2>

<p>The biggest thing I&rsquo;ve repeatedly learned over the past decade of Python conferences is that we&rsquo;re all just people.</p>

<p>Carol Willing keynoted PyCon US 2023.
But I met Carol as a kind Python user in San Diego who started the first Python study group meetings in Pangea Bakery on Convoy Street.</p>

<p>Jay Miller will be keynoting PyCon US 2024.
But I met Jay as an attendee of the Python study group, who was enthusiastic about both learning and teaching others.</p>

<p>My partner, Melanie Arbor, keynoted DjangoCon 2022 along with Jay Miller.
When I met Melanie, she was new to Python and was very eager to both learn and help others.</p>

<p>David Lord has made a huge impact on the maintenance of Flask and other Pallets projects.
I met David as a Python study group attendee who was an enthusiastic StackOverflow contributor.</p>

<p>I learned a ton from Brandon Rhodes, Ned Batchelder, Russell Keith-Magee, and many others from online videos, forums, and open source projects before I ever met them.
But each of them are also just Python-loving people like the rest of us.
Russell gives good hugs, Ned is an organizer of his local Python meetup, and Brandon wears the same brand of shoes as me.</p>

<p>We all have people we&rsquo;ve learned from, we suffer from feelings of inadequacy, we get grumpy sometimes, and we care about the Python language and community in big and small ways.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s next for you?</h2>

<p>Will you attend a local meetup?
Or will you attend an online social event?</p>

<p>If so, consider asking the organize if you can present a 5 minute lightning talk at a future event.
As I <a href="https://youtu.be/aNHBr7q-KVw?si=Fryj6Ez4Cw7q-RAq">noted in a DjangoCon 2016 lightning talk</a>, lightning talks are a great way to connect with folks.</p>

<p>Will you attend a Python conference one day?
See <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2018/04/how-to-make-the-most-of-your-first-pycon/">having a great first PyCon</a> when/if you do.</p>

<p>Remember that we&rsquo;re all just people though.
Some may have a bit more experience (whether at speaking, contributing to open source, or something else), but we&rsquo;re just people.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making the most of the PyCon sprints]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2019/04/making-the-most-of-the-pycon-sprints/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-02T09:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2019/04/making-the-most-of-the-pycon-sprints</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote a blog post last year, <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2018/04/how-to-make-the-most-of-your-first-pycon/">How to have a great first PyCon</a>, in which I gave quite a few tips for <strong>making the most of your time at PyCon</strong> (if you&rsquo;re a first time PyCon attendee, <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2018/04/how-to-make-the-most-of-your-first-pycon/">go read it</a>).
One thing I didn&rsquo;t mention <em>at all</em> in that article on PyCon was <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2019/community/sprints/">the sprints</a>.</p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t mention the sprints not because I don&rsquo;t like them (I actually love the sprints and I usually attend at least the first two days of sprints every year), but because <strong>first-time PyCon attendees often don&rsquo;t stay for the sprints</strong>.
This is partly because the sprints can be very intimidating for first-time PyCon attendees.
The fear that <strong>the sprints aren&rsquo;t for me</strong> is a very real one.</p>

<p>This year PyCon has multiple options to help you have a successful sprint, including their annual &ldquo;Introduction to Sprinting Workshop&rdquo; on Sunday and, brand-new this year, the <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2019/hatchery/mentoredsprints/">mentored sprints</a> a hatchery track for underrepresented beginners.
The applications for the mentored sprints have closed for PyCon 2019, but that&rsquo;s something to keep an eye on for future PyCons.</p>

<p>In this post I&rsquo;m going to share some advice for <strong>how to get the most out of the PyCon sprints</strong> and I hope to <strong>address the fears that folks often feel</strong>. I&rsquo;m hoping this post might encourage you to add an extra day or two to your PyCon trip and give the sprints a try.</p>

<p>The sprints are a very different experience from the talk days at PyCon and <strong>they&rsquo;re hard to compare to the rest of PyCon</strong>.
Some people like the talks better, but I&rsquo;ve also talked to first time sprinters who said <strong>the sprints were their favorite part of the conference</strong>.</p>

<p>In this post I&rsquo;m going to share some advice for <strong>how to get the most out of the PyCon sprints</strong>.
I&rsquo;m hoping this post might encourage you to add an extra day or two to your PyCon trip and give the sprints a try.</p>

<ol data-toc=".entry-content"></ol>


<h2>Your fears going into the sprints</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;re going to start by addressing some common concerns.
I&rsquo;ve heard these concerns from folks I&rsquo;ve encouraged to stay for the sprints and from folks I&rsquo;ve interviewed about their advice for first-time sprinters.</p>

<h3>I&rsquo;m not experienced enough</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve <strong>never contributed to an open source project before</strong> and I don&rsquo;t really know what to do.
I&rsquo;m a <strong>junior programmer</strong> and I&rsquo;m afraid I&rsquo;m not experienced enough.
I <strong>don&rsquo;t write code for a living</strong> and I&rsquo;m afraid I won&rsquo;t be able to get anything done because I don&rsquo;t know how to <em>do</em> much yet.</p>

<p>The sprints are a great place for a first-time open source contributor.
Making a contribution to an open source project <strong>while sitting next to the maintainer</strong> is a unique experience.
If you contribute to open source at home or at work, you&rsquo;re unlikely to have a project maintainer nearby.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a junior programmer or you don&rsquo;t code for a living <strong>you might be afraid of your inexperience</strong>: maybe you&rsquo;re pretty new to coding in general and you don&rsquo;t understand git, testing, version control, and GitHub.
But there&rsquo;s very likely a project for <em>you</em> to contribute to.
The sprints include sprint coordinators who can help <strong>point you to projects they&rsquo;ve heard are particularly beginner-friendly</strong> or who have quite a bit of <strong>low-hanging fruit in their issue tracker for newcomers to dig into</strong> (something as simple as updating the on-boarding documentation can be a great benefit to maintainers).</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;ll be too fast-paced for me</h3>

<p>You might think the sprints involve smart people coding for many hours on end, racing against the clock.
This is false.
From my experience, sprints usually aren&rsquo;t like that at all.</p>

<p>There are some very smart people at the sprints, but there are a lot of newcomers too.
Everyone at the sprints is new to <em>something</em> and most of us are <a href="https://youtu.be/hIJdFxYlEKE?t=333">mediocre programmers</a> (who are more skilled in some areas and less skilled in others).</p>

<p>The &ldquo;pace&rdquo; of the sprints is really up to you.
The name &ldquo;sprints&rdquo; is kind of a misnomer: <strong>I never find myself <em>sprinting</em> while at the sprints</strong>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve attended at least one day of sprints at PyCon US for each of the last 5 years and my sprint experience has almost always consisted of:</p>

<ul>
<li>Some <strong>high level conversation</strong> about an intriguing feature, topic, or idea</li>
<li>Some <strong>low level conversation</strong> about how pieces of a project work (conversations about the inner-workings of a project are so much easier to have in-person)</li>
<li>Some <strong>writing time</strong>.  Sometimes this is writing code.  Sometimes this is writing text copy for documentation or marketing material.  Sometimes it&rsquo;s my own writing time for a talk or article I&rsquo;m working on.</li>
<li>Some <strong>rubber duck time</strong>.  I often wander around asking people what they&rsquo;re working on and sometimes act as their <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging">rubber duck</a>.  I also often wander around seeking my own rubber duck if I get stuck on a particular topic or idea (whether on my own personal project or an open source project I&rsquo;m contributing to).</li>
<li>Plenty of <strong>personal break time</strong>.  I very often take mental breaks during the sprints to wander the halls, often aimlessly.  Breaks feel great, but they also often help my subconscious work on a task for a bit while my conscious mind rests.</li>
</ul>


<p>Sprints are what you make them: some people prefer many hours of furious coding with their earbuds in most of the day but many people prefer something that looks a bit more like <strong>coworking with new friends in a coffee shop</strong>. Sprints are an intense experience for some people, but they don&rsquo;t have to be intense for you.</p>

<p>My sprints are often more relaxed than the conference and many of the best conversations I have during PyCon come out of the sprints.</p>

<h3>I won&rsquo;t be able to get enough done while I&rsquo;m there</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re only planning to be at the sprints for one day, <strong>can you really expect to get up to speed quickly enough to accomplish something meaningful</strong>?</p>

<p>This fear is very real for all sprint attendees.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re just getting started on contributing to a new (to you) code base, <strong>you may not be able to submit a viable change (often in the form of a pull request) by the end of the day</strong>.</p>

<p>This fear is about framing: <strong>what is your goal at the sprints</strong>?</p>

<p>If your goal is to get a pull request merged into an open source project by the end of the day, try to find something minor that needs fixing in the documentation, website styling, or something else that the project maintainer agrees needs fixing.
It&rsquo;s much easier to <strong>get a minor change merged</strong> if you get an early start and pick a small issue.</p>

<p>But if your goal is to make a more substantial improvement to a project, then you probably won&rsquo;t get much code merged (if any) by the end of the day.
For bigger changes, you&rsquo;ll likely <strong>start your work at the sprints and continue it at home</strong>, often with help from the project maintainers (via comments on pull request and/or emails).</p>

<h2>What to expect from the sprints</h2>

<p>What can you really expect while attending the sprints?
What is sprinting really like?</p>

<h3>Some projects are easier to sprint on than others</h3>

<p>Different projects sprint in different ways.
Many projects <strong>go out of their way to welcome contributions from newcomers</strong>, some projects may struggle a little in welcoming newcomers, and a few projects might hold a sprint that&rsquo;s focused entirely on engaging existing contributors since they might not meet to work in-person often (but you&rsquo;re unlikely to stumble upon those).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re not sure what project you&rsquo;d like to sprint on during first day at the sprints, <strong>I recommend picking a project to sprint on that seems particularly newcomer friendly</strong>.
The <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2019/community/sprints/">Pycon Sprints page</a> has several projects that will be sprinting and after the conference ends on Sunday evening you&rsquo;ll get a chance to hear many of the sprinting projects come on stage and tell you who they are and how you can help.
Alternatively (or additionally), if you&rsquo;ve identified a project that particularly suits your interests, <strong>talk to the maintainers</strong> and see if they think (and you think) their project would be a good fit for you.</p>

<p>Keep in mind that <strong>newer projects and smaller projects often have more to be done</strong>.
It can be quite challenging to find issues that need fixing in big and stable projects like CPython and Django, but newer or smaller projects often need more help.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also usually more fun to be <strong>a big fish in a small pond</strong> rather than a small fish in a big pond.
It might take you the same amount of effort to make a small improvement to a big project as it takes to make a big change to a small project.</p>

<h3>The maintainers are there to help you</h3>

<p>During the sprints, project maintainers are there to help you.
Project maintainers can quietly write code at home, but it&rsquo;s hard for them to encourage <em>you</em> to quietly write code at home.
So <strong>many project maintainers consider it their primary responsibility to help you contribute to their project during the sprints</strong>.</p>

<p>The maintainers of projects are usually focused on <strong>enabling your contributions during the sprints</strong> because they want your help.
If you contribute to a project during the sprints, it&rsquo;s more likely you&rsquo;ll decide to contribute to the project again <em>after</em> the sprints.
That would be great for the maintainers (they&rsquo;re getting your help) and might be quite fun for you too.</p>

<p>You might be thinking &ldquo;surely, the maintainers can&rsquo;t be there entirely to help me&rdquo;.
And you&rsquo;re right: a number of maintainers do contribute code to their own projects during the sprints.
Generally the amount of code maintainers commit to their projects increases as the sprints stretch on.
There are far fewer people on the third and fourth days of sprints than on the first and second days.
If a maintainer stays for all four days of the sprints, they&rsquo;re much more likely to commit code to their own project as the number of sprinters working on their project dwindles and as those still working start to need a bit less help than they did on the first day.
<strong>During the first couple days of the sprints, most maintainers are there primarily to help you</strong>.</p>

<h3>The sprints can be more relaxing than the talks</h3>

<p>The talk days of PyCon can be pretty overwhelming.
<strong>The sprints are a bit more structured</strong> (in a sort of odd semi-structured way) because everyone at the sprints is working on something together (or at least they&rsquo;re working on something <em>and</em> they&rsquo;re together).</p>

<p>The sprints are <strong>sort of like an introvert party</strong>: everyone is sitting at tables next to each other, sometimes talking and sometimes working quietly, but always sitting next to other humans without the need to constantly talk and interact.
And even if you&rsquo;re <em>not</em> working on the same thing as someone else, <strong>you&rsquo;re still a PyCon person in a room with other PyCon people, doing whatever it is you&rsquo;re all doing</strong>.</p>

<p>For some people the sprints really are a sprint, but for most of us <strong>the sprints are more like an endurance run</strong>, one with <em>plenty</em> of breaks.</p>

<h3>Contributing at the sprints is often easier than online</h3>

<p><strong>Contributing to open source projects at the sprints is usually easier than contributing online</strong>.
The ease of in-person communication often makes the experience less intimidating.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s easier to express oneself and empathize during face-to-face communication than over text-based communication.
Emoji are great, but they&rsquo;re not a substitute for body language and tone of voice.</p>

<p>It feels less awkward to chat with a project maintainer about your goals and your skill level in-person than via a GitHub pull request.</p>

<p>Little bits of seemingly meaningless conversation happen while folks sit next to each other for hours: conversation about weather, hobbies, what we thought of our lunch, pop culture, and whatever else comes up.
That kind of natural conversation brings people closer together and makes us feel more comfortable communicating later, whether in-person or online.</p>

<p>Continued communication online is also often easier <em>after</em> face-to-face communication.
After you&rsquo;ve met a project maintainer in-person, you&rsquo;ll likely find communicating online via their issue tracker less intimidating because <strong>you and the maintainer already know each other</strong>.</p>

<p>The in-person nature of the sprints makes them a uniquely favorable place for your first open source contribution.</p>

<h2>How to get the most out of the sprints</h2>

<p>The sprints are a unique experience that <em>might</em> give you a greater sense of community, purpose, and belonging than the (often not quite as communal) talk days of the conference.</p>

<p>What steps can you take to increase the likelihood that you&rsquo;ll have a wonderful time at the PyCon sprints?</p>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t underestimate your skills</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re trying to get a feel for what project might be a good fit for you, let the maintainers know what skills you do and don&rsquo;t have and <strong>see if you get a good vibe</strong> from both the maintainers and the project.
If you do, run with it!</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re afraid you won&rsquo;t have something to contribute, remember that, like businesses, <strong>open source projects have a wide variety of needs</strong>.</p>

<p>If you know something about marketing, you can offer to sit with project maintainers and <strong>help them improve their marketing materials</strong>.
At PyCon 2016 I interviewed some project maintainers and then crafted slogans and wrote marketing copy that explained what problem their project solved and who needed it.
I feel those were some of the most valuable contributions I made in a pretty short amount of time.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re pretty good at design, you could offer to <strong>create visuals for projects</strong> (maybe logos, diagrams, or other visualizations).</p>

<p>If you know CSS or JavaScript, you could find <strong>a web-based project that needs help with their front-end</strong>.
Being the &ldquo;front-end dev among Pythonistas&rdquo; or the &ldquo;UX person among developers&rdquo; can really help you make uniquely helpful contributions to projects.</p>

<p>Also keep in mind that there are often small projects that you can make big contributions to at the sprints simply because they&rsquo;re in great need.
Sometimes people even start a project <em>at the sprints</em> because it&rsquo;s easier to get help from others when <strong>you&rsquo;re in a room full of folks who might know a few things about the technology you&rsquo;re using</strong>.
If you join a newer or smaller project at the sprints (or start your own), you&rsquo;ll often be able to find a whole bunch of low-hanging fruit that hasn&rsquo;t been taken care of only because no one has had the time to work on it yet.</p>

<h3>Attend the intro to the sprints the night before</h3>

<p>Some maintainers list their projects on the <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2019/community/sprints/">PyCon sprints page</a> to note that they&rsquo;ll be attending the sprints.
Some maintainers simply announce their project during <strong>the sprint pitches after</strong> the main conference closing, on the last day of talks (Sunday).
If you are looking for a project, stick around after the last talk of the day and dozens of maintainers will walk up on the big stage to give an elevator pitch for the project they&rsquo;re sprinting on, with each pitch taking about a minute.</p>

<p>During the sprint pitches, each maintainer will talk about what their project is, what kind of help they&rsquo;re most in need of (fitting as much as they can in the very few seconds they have) and generally close with some commentary on whether their project is a good fit for newcomers.
You don&rsquo;t have to attend the sprint pitches, but doing so will increase your chances of hearing about <strong>a project that you&rsquo;d actually really like to work on</strong>.</p>

<p>Another thing to pay attention to on the last day of talks is the hands-on <strong>Introduction to Sprinting tutorial</strong> on Sunday evening.
The Intro to Sprinting tutorial is open to walk-ins (first-come, first-served) and is purposely held after the main conference closing so you won&rsquo;t need to miss any talks.</p>

<p>Last year the Intro to Sprinting tutorial room filled up pretty quickly, so rest assured you won&rsquo;t be alone.
Definitely try to get the Intro to Sprinting workshop on your calendar (once the room and time are announced) and show up on-time if you can.</p>

<h3>Try to prepare yourself for the setup time</h3>

<p>Getting started on a new project can take a lot of time, so try to prepare yourself and your development environment as much as you can early on.</p>

<p>Make sure you have git, GitHub, a code editor, and a modern version (maybe multiple versions) of Python installed on your machine.</p>

<p><strong>Get an early start if possible</strong>.
The setup process can take a long time for some projects. Many projects will have a documentation page set up with instructions on what to install and how to install it. But be aware&hellip; sometimes the setup process is a little buggy and <strong>the first pull request you make to a project may be related to improving the setup instructions</strong>.</p>

<p>If you show up to sprints early, you might be able to pick a project and get that project setup on your machine before break time.
If you&rsquo;re feeling extra ambitious, <strong>you could even get a head start and prepare your machine the night before the sprints</strong>.
I&rsquo;ve never done this because I&rsquo;m rarely feeling ambitious, but I know some folks do this to make sure they can get in a little more quality sprinting time on the first day.</p>

<p>Another way to prepare yourself for setup time is to stay longer.
If you&rsquo;re staying for 2 or 3 days of sprints, you can take it easy and spend more time on setup and getting your footing during the first day.
That way you&rsquo;ll feel <strong>more confident and more independent on the second day</strong>.
If you stay more than one day, you might also get the opportunity to <strong>sprint on two different projects</strong> if you decide you&rsquo;d like to switch projects on day 2 (or even mid-day if you&rsquo;d like).</p>

<p>Oh and another way to prepare yourself: remember your laptop and your laptop charger (and if you&rsquo;re from outside the US, a power adapter if needed).</p>

<h3>Ask for help</h3>

<p>If the maintainer of the project your sprinting on is in the room they&rsquo;re likely there because <strong>they want to help you contribute to their project</strong>.
On day 1 of sprints, project maintainers tend to prioritize helping you, over writing their own code.
<strong>Please don&rsquo;t forget to ask for help when you need it</strong>.</p>

<p>Also if you&rsquo;re stuck on laptop setup issues, the PyCon sprint coordinators will be hosting <strong>a help desk during the first day of sprints</strong> (on Monday).
The help desk is a great place to get yourself unstuck when you have a general issue that could use another set of eyes.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re at the sprints to learn, you do want to struggle <em>some</em>.
Struggling is a great way to learn, but don&rsquo;t let yourself flounder for too long on issues that aren&rsquo;t your area of expertise.
If you get stuck, attempt to fix your problem by trial-and-error and Googling, talk to your neighbor or your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging">rubber duck</a> and <strong>after you&rsquo;ve given yourself some time to troubleshoot, ask for help</strong>!</p>

<h3>Plan to follow-through when home (if you&rsquo;d like)</h3>

<p>Keep in mind that you may not complete your work at the sprints.
You&rsquo;re likely to find yourself <strong>still in the middle of a pull request back-and-forth at the end of your sprints</strong>.
Pull requests often require more work before merging.
Expect to get started at the sprints, but not necessarily to finish while you&rsquo;re there.</p>

<p>If you plan to complete your pull request at home, <strong>ask the project maintainer what form of remote communication would be best for questions you have regarding contributions</strong>.</p>

<h3>Empathize with others</h3>

<p>Your project maintainer may not show up early on day 1 and they might even leave early, depending on what their plans and schedule look like.
If they&rsquo;re at the Sunday night pitches or if you interact with them during PyCon, you might consider asking them when they plan to be present and how they plan to operate (will they be writing code or helping others write code or both).</p>

<p>When sprinting, try to empathize with your project maintainer.
Empathy is challenging during remote open source contributions, but it can be a struggle even for in-person contributions.</p>

<p>Consider what your project maintainer&rsquo;s motivations likely are and remember that they&rsquo;re often trying to balance <strong>getting many new contributors to their project</strong>, <strong>getting bugs fixed</strong>, and <strong>maintaining the quality and consistency of their code base</strong>.
Balancing multiple goals which sometimes compete with each other can be a challenge.</p>

<p>Text-based communication is hard, so <strong>seize your face-to-face communication while you&rsquo;re at the sprints</strong> and try to get a sense for how your project maintainer thinks.
If you do decide to contribute more after the sprints are over, <strong>that in-person empathy can help you continue to empathize remotely as well</strong>.</p>

<p>Some other places you may want to use empathy: empathizing with users of your code/documentation/design (someone is going to use your work) and the other sprinters in the room with you.
It&rsquo;s nice to congratulate your fellow sprinters when they get their code working or if they get a pull request accepted.</p>

<p>If you bring snacks, candy, donuts, or a small power strip to expand one power strip port into multiple, <strong>your kindness might give you happy neighbors at the sprints</strong>.</p>

<h3>Be kind to yourself</h3>

<p>Don&rsquo;t go into the sprints with a very specific thing that you absolutely must do: have a goal but <strong>allow yourself to change your goal</strong> as you learn new information about your environment.
<strong>Be flexible and be forgiving with yourself</strong>.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;re allowed to <strong>switch projects</strong> at any time, as often as you like, and for any reason you like (i.e. the project isn&rsquo;t as interesting as you hoped, the onboarding process isn&rsquo;t as smooth as you expected, or the project isn&rsquo;t a good fit for you).
If you need to switch projects, don&rsquo;t feel you need to offer elaborate explanations.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;re allowed to <strong>stop sprinting</strong> at any time and <strong>take a break</strong>.
You aren&rsquo;t obligated to follow through on a pull request you opened (it&rsquo;d be lovely if you did, but you don&rsquo;t <em>have</em> to).</p>

<p>Time-wise, there&rsquo;s lots of flexibility at the sprints.
The maintainer of the project you&rsquo;re sprinting on might get an early start or they might not show up until later on the first day of sprints.
You need to give yourself flexibility as well.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t feel obligated at the sprints: you don&rsquo;t have to make a code change, <strong>you don&rsquo;t have to be productive</strong>, you don&rsquo;t have to show up at a certain time or stay for a certain amount of time, and <strong>you don&rsquo;t even have to sprint on an open source project</strong> (I frequently don&rsquo;t).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;d like to take half of a sprint day to explore the city you&rsquo;re in with a new friend (or on your own because you need personal time), go for it!</p>

<p>Embrace self-care at the sprints, whatever that means for you.</p>

<h3>Remember that sprints are lots of things to lots of people</h3>

<p>During my first PyCon sprint in 2014, I helped a project figure out how to migrate from Python 2 to Python 3.
The project maintainer wasn&rsquo;t looking forward to that migration so they were grateful to have another brain troubleshooting with them.</p>

<p>But during that sprint I also got an idea for a contribution to another project (Django), was encouraged to pursue the idea, and <a href="https://github.com/django/deps/pull/4">a few weeks after the sprints</a> I proposed the idea publicly.
After my suggestion sat without feedback, I sort of abandoned it.</p>

<p>But at the PyCon 2015 sprints the next year, I brought up my abandoned idea to a Django core developer and they offered to shepherd my change through, so I <a href="https://github.com/django/deps/pull/13">continued my efforts</a> during the sprints.
A couple weeks after the sprints ended I <a href="https://github.com/django/deps/pull/14">finished up the idea at home</a> and finally <a href="https://github.com/django/django/pull/4573">implemented the changes</a>, which were eventually merged (after <a href="https://github.com/django/deps/pull/15/files">some scope tweaks</a>).</p>

<p>My first two years of PyCon sprints involved some substantial code contributions that I hadn&rsquo;t expected to make.
Most of the changes I made were <strong>started at the sprints but finished at home</strong>.</p>

<p>The sprints were a source of idea generation and inspiration, not a place to get lots of work done.
Since 2015 I&rsquo;ve started sprinting on <em>ideas</em> more than code.</p>

<p>During my PyCon 2016 sprints I helped a few open source projects improve their marketing copy (so someone hitting their website would better understand what their project did and who it was for).
My pull requests during these sprints were text-based changes, not code changes.</p>

<p>My PyCon 2017 sprints involved a lot of community work: discussions with folks about the PSF and the new Code of Conduct working group.
I spent much more time in Google Docs tweaking documents than I did using git.</p>

<p>My sprints at PyCon 2018 involved writing talk proposals, meeting with new friends, and chatting with core developers about the soon-to-be-written <a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0582/">PEP 582</a>.
I don&rsquo;t think I made any contributions to open source projects (outside of possibly inspiring a bullet point or two in that PEP).
But I had a great time and sitting quietly in the sprint rooms helped me get a lot of work done on my talk proposals.</p>

<p><strong>The sprints aren&rsquo;t one thing</strong>.
If you&rsquo;re not feeling like a code contribution is the thing you&rsquo;d like to do during the sprints, get creative!
<strong>Your time at the sprints can be spent however you&rsquo;d like it to be</strong>.</p>

<h2>Running your own sprint</h2>

<p>This could be a whole article on its own, but I want to give a few quick tips for folks who might be attempting to run a sprint for their own project.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;ve maintained open source projects remotely, I haven&rsquo;t run an in-person sprint on my own projects.
So my tips on running a sprint on your own project come from the perspective of a contributor and a floating helper for maintainers who needed an extra hand.</p>

<p>As a project maintainer on day 1 of sprints, <strong>I&rsquo;d consider your primary responsibility to be one of helping encourage other contributors</strong>.
You want to help folks get their environment setup, help folks identify good issues to work on, help folks with their code contributions, and even help other contributors as they help out their neighbors.</p>

<p><strong>Your job often isn&rsquo;t to write code</strong>, it&rsquo;s to be <em>interrupted</em> by people who are trying to make contributions but need your help.</p>

<p>For the in-person, in-the-moment part of running a sprint I have <a href="http://trey.io/pycascades2019">a whole talk and a bunch of related resources</a> for folks who are coaching others in-person.
But your job doesn&rsquo;t start <em>at the sprints</em>.
Ideally, you&rsquo;ll want to <strong>prepare your project for the sprints</strong> a while before the sprints even start.</p>

<p>Many projects use issue labels to indicate <strong>issues which are specifically good for first-time contributors</strong> (something like &ldquo;newcomer&rdquo;, &ldquo;good first issue&rdquo;, &ldquo;first-timers only&rdquo;, etc.).
I&rsquo;d recommend looking at <a href="https://github.com/MunGell/awesome-for-beginners#python">the many other contributor-friendly projects</a>, studying what they do, and figuring out <strong>how you can make your project more friendly to new sprinters</strong>.</p>

<p>The PyCon sprints page also recommends this <a href="https://opensourceevents.github.io/">in-person events handbook</a> made by the OpenHatch folks.
Take a look at it!
And if you can, <strong>ask questions of other project maintainers you admire who will also be sprinting</strong>: how do they ensure newcomers feel appreciated, how do they help folks feel accomplished, what do they do to get their project and their minds ready?</p>

<h2>Take note of the key events</h2>

<p>Put the events you&rsquo;ll be attending for the PyCon 2019 sprints in your calendar!</p>

<p>The sprint pitches are on the last talk day at PyCon, just after the closing of the main conference.
The Intro to Sprints tutorial usually starts just after that.
And during the first day of sprints the next day, the sprint help desk will be available to help you get some extra help on day 1.</p>

<p>Also remember the mentored sprints (if you&rsquo;ve gone through the application process already) which are designed for underrepresented groups and are on Saturday during the talks.</p>

<h2>Ask others what they think of the sprints</h2>

<p>Much of the above advice was borrowed or enhanced by wisdom from others.
I&rsquo;ve held interviews with folks during the last few PyCon sprints, I&rsquo;ve asked folks online what they think of the sprints, and I&rsquo;ve chatted with first-time sprinters about what their concerns were going into the sprints.
If you shared your sprint experiences with me in the past, thank you.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re still uncertain about whether you should attend a sprint, please talk to others about what they think of the PyCon sprints.
I&rsquo;ve found that most PyCon attendees are more than happy to talk about their perspective on the various parts of the conference they&rsquo;ve partaken in.</p>

<p>If you can&rsquo;t afford to stay for the sprints, I completely understand.
Most PyCon attendees will not be staying for the sprints.
But if you&rsquo;re lucky enough to have the time and resources to stay, I&rsquo;d suggest giving it a try.</p>

<p>If you can afford to schedule some extra time to attend a day or two of sprints and then decide that the sprints aren&rsquo;t for you, that time could always be spent exploring the city you&rsquo;re in, working, or doing something else that makes you feel whole.</p>

<p>And if you&rsquo;re from an underrepresented or marginalized group in tech and you&rsquo;re new to sprinting, consider applying for the <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2019/hatchery/mentoredsprints/">mentored sprints</a> for PyCon 2020.</p>

<p>Whatever you decide, have a lovely PyCon! 💖</p>

<p>Thanks to Asheesh Laroia for encouraging this post and Chalmer Lowe for quite a bit of helpful feedback while I was writing it.
Thanks also to the many folks who sent me ideas and shared their perspective and advice about the sprints.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to have a great first PyCon]]></title>
    <link href="https://treyhunner.com/2018/04/how-to-make-the-most-of-your-first-pycon/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-30T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://treyhunner.com/2018/04/how-to-make-the-most-of-your-first-pycon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Update (2024)</strong>: I&rsquo;ve updated the links for PyCon US 2024.
Also if this isn&rsquo;t your first time attending a conference but it <em>is</em> your first PyCon, also see <strong><a href="https://www.harihareswara.net/posts/2023/your-first-pycon-but-not-your-first-convention/">Your First PyCon, But Not Your First Convention</a></strong> by Sumana Harihareswara (who is <em>keynoting PyCon 2024</em> this year!).</p>

<p><strong>Update (2019)</strong>: I originally left the sprints out of this article completely!
To remedy that, I&rsquo;ve recently published another article <a href="https://treyhunner.com/2019/04/making-the-most-of-the-pycon-sprints/">all about the PyCon sprints</a> and why you should consider attending them.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ve decided to invest energy, money, and time away from your home so that you can go to your first PyCon.
Now you want to make sure you spend your time wisely by attending events relevant to you and possibly by forming relations with other PyCon attendees.
But you&rsquo;re (naturally) not an expert conference-goer.
How do you do this?
How do you make the most of your first PyCon?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m an introvert by nature, but I have increased my ability to socialize with others over the years through practice, gamification of social situations, and learning my limits.</p>

<p>Over the last few years, I&rsquo;ve interviewed many PyCon attendees on <a href="http://weeklypython.chat">Weekly Python Chat</a> and I&rsquo;ve spoken with many first-time PyCon-goers about making the most of PyCon.
It&rsquo;s difficult to describe what PyCon is like to first-time attendees and it&rsquo;s even more difficult to identify how any one person should spend their time at PyCon.
So I&rsquo;m writing this article to compile some of the advice I&rsquo;ve heard from others and to address some of the common fears I hear among first-time PyCon attendees.
Not all of the suggestions below will be right for you, so try to take the advice that works well for you.</p>

<p>Before you read any further, I have to link you to the <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2024/events/newcomer-orientation/">Newcomer Orientation</a>.
This is a new event hosted by Adrienne Lowe this year.
If this is your first PyCon, I&rsquo;d definitely recommend showing up early to the newcomer orientation and get your footing before the big event starts.</p>

<p>Have a specific question or just want to <strong>jump to a specific topic</strong>?</p>

<ul data-toc=".entry-content"></ul>


<h2>Spending your time: which talks should I go to? 🤔</h2>

<p>The talks at PyCon are typically <strong>uploaded to YouTube within 24 hours after the talk ends</strong>.
That means that you can spend your evening watching the talks you missed the day before or you can watch the talks when you go home.
I&rsquo;m not suggesting you shouldn&rsquo;t watch talks at PyCon.
I am suggesting that <strong>you don&rsquo;t need to worry about attending every talk</strong>.</p>

<p>So how should I decide which talks to go to?
I&rsquo;ve chatted with folks who purposely go exclusively to talks on topics they&rsquo;re not normally interested in.
I also know people who <strong>love going to the keynotes and the lightning talks</strong> but hang out in the hallway (I&rsquo;ll talk about the hallway track later) or attend open spaces the rest of the time.
I&rsquo;m personally one of those people who <strong>attends very few talks</strong> and spends a lot of time in open spaces and the in hallway.</p>

<p><strong>You cannot and will not do everything there is to do at PyCon</strong>.</p>

<p>I suggest embracing this idea by chatting with others about things you&rsquo;ve missed out on.
<strong>People often enjoy reflecting on a talk they just watched</strong> the same way you might want to reflect on a movie.
If you meet someone who just came out of a talk you missed, ask them what it was like and what they learned from it.
They might say &ldquo;eh, it wasn&rsquo;t for me&rdquo; or they might ramble about how exciting it was.</p>

<p>Consider these things before walking into a talk:</p>

<ul>
<li>Would it be nice to show up to this talk a few minutes early and focus my attention on it?</li>
<li>Do I want to possibly ask the speaker a question during Q&amp;A?  (tips for Q&amp;A <a href="https://kev.inburke.com/kevin/how-not-to-ask-questions-at-conference/">here</a> and <a href="https://networkingnerd.net/2016/11/09/how-to-ask-a-question-at-a-conference/">here</a>)</li>
<li>Am I having a conversation that I&rsquo;d really like to continue instead of attending this talk?</li>
<li>Should I take a personal break during this time instead?</li>
</ul>


<p>Remember that PyCon is less about the talks than the discussions that happen around them.
Talks are a wonderful tool to start discussions, but they&rsquo;re not the only way to spark conversation.</p>

<h2>Open spaces: attend them and consider hosting your own! 👐</h2>

<p><a href="https://us.pycon.org/2024/events/open-spaces/">Open spaces</a> are <strong>community-run mini meetup events and they aren&rsquo;t decided before PyCon starts</strong>.
The way it works is that someone puts an index card on the open spaces board to indicate that they&rsquo;re holding an event at a particular time in one of the open spaces rooms that day.
Then others check the open spaces board throughout the day and attend ones they&rsquo;re interested in.</p>

<p>During every talk at PyCon there are at least 4 other talks happening.
There are also 9 open spaces rooms though.
So you&rsquo;re missing out on over 90% of PyCon at any time!</p>

<p>When choosing between an open space and a talk, I usually choose the open space.</p>

<p>There are a few reasons I often pick open spaces over talks:</p>

<ol>
<li>Often the <strong>open spaces are more niche and topical than the talks</strong>: there are some subjects that exist in open spaces every year but which I&rsquo;ve never seen a talk on</li>
<li><strong>Open spaces are all about interaction and discussion</strong> whereas talks are a monologue that often evolves into subsequent dialogues</li>
<li><strong>Open spaces aren&rsquo;t recorded whereas the talks are</strong>, meaning you can&rsquo;t really catch up on them later</li>
</ol>


<p>If you&rsquo;re looking for kinship and conversation, the open spaces a great place to look.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re hoping to <em>start</em> a discussion, I&rsquo;d also recommend <a href="https://pycon.blogspot.com/2018/04/keep-eye-out-for-open-space-events-at.html">creating your own open space</a> during PyCon.
The PyCon blog will be publishing a post on open spaces soon which I co-authored.</p>

<p>Disclaimed after the fact: I&rsquo;m one of the volunteer open spaces co-chairs, so I&rsquo;m biased in my love for them.</p>

<h2>Feeling like an imposter or an outsider 🌪</h2>

<p>A common fear when attending PyCon is that people will judge you because you aren&rsquo;t as skilled as they are.</p>

<p>Maybe you&rsquo;re new to Python and you&rsquo;re worried your peers won&rsquo;t accept you because you think you might be years-off from matching their skills.
Maybe you&rsquo;re &ldquo;not a developer&rdquo; and you&rsquo;re afraid you&rsquo;ll feel like an imposter at PyCon.</p>

<p>Not feeling like you&rsquo;ll be smart enough or skilled enough to understand the talks and conversations you&rsquo;ll be in is a big and intimidating thought.
If you&rsquo;re afraid of folks misjudging your expertise, it may help to plan out a few techniques for presenting yourself in a way that makes you feel comfortable.</p>

<p>You might rehearse a few different very <strong>brief elevator pitches</strong>.
Here are some examples:</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;m a JavaScript developer here to meet folks in the Python world</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a new programmer and I&rsquo;m here because I&rsquo;ve been told the Python community was pretty welcoming to newcomers</li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t consider myself a developer, but I do write Python code at work to automate things and I&rsquo;m here to learn more</li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t write code for work, but I have some side projects that I&rsquo;m using Python for.  So I&rsquo;m here to learn and meet friendly people.</li>
</ul>


<p>Remember that <strong>you do not need to justify your presence at PyCon</strong>.
If you believe you belong at PyCon, then you do.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in the conversation you&rsquo;re in, others may mirror that interest.
If you&rsquo;re enthusiastic about learning new things, others you meet may mirror that enthusiasm.
I&rsquo;ve witnessed quite a few conversations at PyCon that included phrases like &ldquo;oh you don&rsquo;t know about X?  Cool, essentially it&rsquo;s&hellip;&rdquo;
You&rsquo;ll hopefully find that many of the more long-time PyCon attendees go out of their way to welcome beginners.
This is not a universal phenomenon and even folks with good intentions can alienate those around them.</p>

<h2>Tips for starting conversation 💬</h2>

<p>Make sure to treat each person you meet as new.
<strong>Not everyone you meet will be at the conference for the same reasons as you are</strong>.
Some people write code but don&rsquo;t know Python, some people only using a little bit of Python and don&rsquo;t consider themselves developers, some people don&rsquo;t work in tech, and some people don&rsquo;t write code for work at all and may be considering whether they should make a career transition into tech.
Just as you don&rsquo;t need to justify your presence at PyCon to anyone, no one needs to justify their presence to you.</p>

<p>I mentioned above that you might want to make an elevator pitch or two for yourself.
You might also want to consider how you&rsquo;ll respond to some of the questions that will come up frequently, like &ldquo;what do you do?&rdquo; or &ldquo;where do you work?&rdquo;.
You will be asked some of the same questions over and over when meeting new people.
<strong>Knowing how you&rsquo;ll respond to common questions will help put your mind at ease when meeting new people</strong>.</p>

<p>I also recommend occasionally considering what questions you ask, why you&rsquo;re asking them, and the phrasing you use.
Also notice how others ask questions and consider what questions and phrases seem to put others at ease and lead to interesting conversations.
Conversations often go pretty well if you <strong>ask questions that make others feel comfortable and appreciated</strong>.</p>

<h2>Tips for breakfast and lunch time 🍽</h2>

<p>How do lunch and breakfast work?
Can I just sit with anyone or should I choose an empty table?
Are people going to be nice to me?
Do I need to introduce myself when I sit down?</p>

<p>Meal dynamics are interesting because there&rsquo;s not really a rule book for these social dynamics.
Below is what I&rsquo;ve observed over the years.</p>

<p><strong>At lunch and breakfast, you can sit anywhere</strong>.
Often people will ask &ldquo;is this seat taken&rdquo; when sitting down just in case a group of acquaintances are waiting on another person to join them.
Sometimes when a new person joins your table, a particularly friendly person at the table (if one exists) will introduce themselves to make that newcomer feel welcome.
Often this entails a name, a smile, and a wave or a nod.
Beyond these typical social norms, everything else can differ based on the folks sitting at your table (that includes you!).</p>

<p>Sometimes a couple people at a table will be very interested to know what brings everyone to the conference and what each person &ldquo;does&rdquo;.
<strong>Meals are a good time to test out your elevator pitch</strong> when introducing yourself to see how the conversation goes and to verify that it makes you feel comfortable.</p>

<p>Sometimes people will be more interested in either sitting quietly or talking to a particular person or two with whom they&rsquo;ve found something interesting to discuss.
Personally I often find myself asking others where they&rsquo;re traveling from, whether it&rsquo;s their first year attending, what they&rsquo;ve thought of the conference so far, and <strong>what inspired them to come to PyCon</strong>.
I tend to leave questions about employment and jobs for later because folks will often bring up their work (if they want to) on their own.</p>

<h2>The hallway track 👣</h2>

<p>Something you might consider doing while at PyCon is <strong>taking breaks in the hallway</strong>.
Sit at a table in the open and if someone asks whether they can sit at your table say something inviting/friendly like &ldquo;sure! I&rsquo;m YOUR_NAME. Nice to meet you new friend!&rdquo; (or just smile and gesture in a friendly way if you&rsquo;re not feeling adventurous in the moment).
Chatting with folks in the hallway in an unstructured way is often referred to as the <a href="http://www.ericmjl.com/blog/2016/6/3/the-pycon-ers-guide-to-the-hallway-track/">hallway track</a>.</p>

<p>In addition to joining or starting a table in the hallway, consider identifying groups that have <a href="http://ericholscher.com/blog/2017/aug/2/pacman-rule-conferences/">a PacMan opening</a> to join and make sure the groups you&rsquo;re in are PacMan-friendly.</p>

<p>While chatting with new friends, giving one person your full attention in a 5 minute conversation is often more rewarding and memorable than having five 1 minute conversations with different people.
But do keep in mind though that <strong>if you&rsquo;re no longer interested in a conversation or activity, you don&rsquo;t need to keep it going</strong>.
There are lots of things going on at any one time at PyCon and lots of people there.
It&rsquo;s not unusual to say &ldquo;nice talking to you&rdquo; and leave one conversation to walk off to another conversation or to something else entirely.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t just follow the rules: be compassionate 💖</h2>

<p>You&rsquo;re at a professional event.
You should absolutely try to have fun and derive as much value as you can from PyCon, but you always want to make sure you feel welcome, comfortable, and safe.
Importantly, you should also be mindful to make sure those around you feel the same way.
Please <strong>be cognizant of the preferences of those around you and be respectful of their needs</strong>.</p>

<p>PyCon has a <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2024/about/code-of-conduct/">code of conduct</a>.
Read it.
I expect you to go beyond embracing the law of the code of conduct.
I&rsquo;d like you to embrace the spirit of the code of conduct as well.</p>

<p>When meeting people in general, <strong>make sure to be nice</strong>.
Don&rsquo;t talk down to people, don&rsquo;t insult people, and don&rsquo;t treat anyone like they don&rsquo;t belong or aren&rsquo;t worthy.
<strong>The Python community prides itself on being nice</strong> and we expect you to be nice as well.
Be kind, be compassionate, be considerate.</p>

<p>On that note, you may run into folks who act unkind or make you feel unwelcome at some point.
It&rsquo;s okay to cut and run at any point during any conversation or event.
If you don&rsquo;t feel welcome, I recommend <strong>removing yourself from the space you&rsquo;re in and contacting one of the staff members</strong> listed on <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2024/about/code-of-conduct/">the code of conduct page</a>.
Even if you just want to say &ldquo;hey something happened that could maybe be avoided in the future,&rdquo; it would be wonderful if you could muster the courage to contact a staff member.
<strong>PyCon tries to improve every year and feedback is the way that happens</strong>.</p>

<h2>Interacting online during PyCon 🐦</h2>

<p>After PyCon is over, some people occasionally follow-up with folks they met over email.
Sometimes people will add each other on LinkedIn or Facebook also.
But the means of interaction I&rsquo;ve noticed most is Twitter.
I&rsquo;m unlikely to send most of the people I meet at PyCon an email, but I try to add most of the people I meet to my <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/lists/pycon-2017/members">PyCon list</a> on Twitter.</p>

<p><strong>2024 note</strong>: Twitter is not nearly as active as it was when I originally wrote this post.
I now use a mix of Twitter and Mastodon, though I&rsquo;m sure some folks will be on Threads, Bluesky, or some other real-time online social network as well.
Unfortunately, there&rsquo;s no one network anymore. 🤷</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re not completely opposed to it, <strong>I recommend getting Mastodon and/or Twitter accounts to make it easier to passively keep up with folks from PyCon after the conference ends</strong>.
You don&rsquo;t have to use these networks all the time to get value from it, you could just use it as a modern day <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolodex">rolodex</a> of sorts.
Online social networks are not the only way people stay in touch, but it&rsquo;s an extremely easy passive way to stay in touch.</p>

<p>If you do get a Mastodon and/or Twitter account, I recommend adding a saved search for &ldquo;PyCon2024 OR PyCon OR PyConUS OR PyConUS2024&rdquo; to your to <strong>follow a bit of the random PyCon-related Twitter chatter during the conference</strong> and to like/reply/interact with others online.
I know I will be adding the <code>#PyConUS</code> hashtag to my Mastodon feed while at the conference this year!</p>

<p>Sometimes <strong>people on social networks will ask if anyone would like to join them for dinner</strong> and you might decide to reply and say you&rsquo;d like to join.
Sometimes you&rsquo;ll recognize the face or name of someone you met over breakfast or someone you recognize from another part of the internet.
If you&rsquo;re feeling comfortable with it, you could send a tweet to that person to ask if they&rsquo;d like to meet up and chat during one of the breaks.</p>

<p>However, I keep in mind when you meet people that people are just people.
If you think someone is famous or important or smart, don&rsquo;t treat them like they&rsquo;re a celebrity or like they&rsquo;re superior to you.
<strong>It&rsquo;s wonderful to show appreciation for what someone does</strong>.
But keep in mind that <strong>most people feel awkward when they feel like they&rsquo;re being put on a pedestal</strong>.
Treat folks you meet as your equals.</p>

<h2>Networking isn&rsquo;t a dirty word: it means making friends 👥</h2>

<p>I hear two opposing concerns sometimes expressed about PyCon:</p>

<ol>
<li>Isn&rsquo;t everyone here to get a job or hire people?</li>
<li>Is it acceptable to go to PyCon looking for a job?</li>
</ol>


<p>PyCon is a networking event.
That doesn&rsquo;t necessarily mean everyone is there to get a job, but it also definitely doesn&rsquo;t mean it&rsquo;s unacceptable to job-seek at Python.</p>

<p>There is <strong>no shame in going to PyCon with the goal of getting a new job</strong>.
Many of the sponsors in the Expo hall are looking to hire new developers and events like the job fair are specifically designed to bring together folks seeking work and folks seeking workers.
But <strong>if you are not at PyCon to get a job or to hire someone else, that&rsquo;s absolutely okay also</strong>!</p>

<p>The focus of PyCon is on <strong>meeting people and sharing experiences</strong> and that can come in a <em>lot</em> of different forms.
Sometimes the people you meet will end up being your coworkers one day, sometimes they&rsquo;re folks you&rsquo;d like to keep in touch with, and sometimes they&rsquo;re just a friendly unnamed Pythonistas you once had a good conversation with.</p>

<p>PyCon is a networking event and networking isn&rsquo;t a dirty word.
<strong>Networking means meeting new people</strong>.
I&rsquo;ve met a <em>lot</em> of people at PyCon who I care deeply about.
Some of them I haven&rsquo;t seen in years and only keep in touch with sporadically through social media, some I see once or twice each year, and some I chat with on a weekly basis online.</p>

<p>Whatever your goals are at PyCon, try <strong>savor the experiences you have</strong> while there.</p>

<h2>Be prepared to keep in touch 📇</h2>

<p>How am I supposed to remember all these amazing people I met!
Should I bring business cards and if so how many?
How should I follow up with people after the conference?</p>

<p>If you have a good conversation with someone, I&rsquo;d recommend exchanging information with them.
I&rsquo;ve seen people <strong>write email addresses on napkins</strong>.
I&rsquo;ve also frequently seen people exchange business cards or name cards.
Sometimes people simply <strong>write down Twitter/Mastodon/LinkedIn handles</strong> or even ask to take a picture of a face and a badge.
As I noted above, I like to get people&rsquo;s Twitter handles and add them to a <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/lists/pycon-2017/members">PyCon list</a> I maintain for myself.
I also exchange business cards and other forms of contact information.</p>

<p>Being handed a business card doesn&rsquo;t mean &ldquo;this is a business interaction and we are fancy business people&rdquo;.
If someone hands you a business card, it usually means they appreciated the conversation they had with you and they&rsquo;d like to keep in touch (or at least allow for that possibility).
Sometimes it means they want to hire you, but often they simply want a way to remember your name so they can find you on social media or send you an email later.</p>

<p>The tricky part is remembering to stay in touch when you go home and remembering which people you had which conversations with.
It&rsquo;s not unusual for people to <strong>take notes on business cards about what they talked about with you and why</strong>.
I think this is a great strategy for remembering who you&rsquo;re most interested in sending a kind note to after you go home and I wish I remembered to do this more often.</p>

<p>This blog post on <a href="http://swombat.com/2011/2/25/kevin-mcdonagh-how-to-attend-a-conference">how to attend a conference</a> has recommendations for staying in touch (as well as many other recommendations).</p>

<h2>Evening events: dinners and board games 🃏</h2>

<p>What do people do for dinner?
How do they organize?
How late do they stay?
Is there dinner at the conference center, if you don&rsquo;t want to go out?
How do I find people to go to dinner with if I don&rsquo;t know anyone?
Also I know that there are some informal get-togethers at the conference.
How do I propose them?
How do I know what&rsquo;s there?</p>

<p>One trick that I&rsquo;ve used and I&rsquo;ve seen others use: <strong>make a game of inviting people you don&rsquo;t really know well to dinner</strong>.
If you&rsquo;re nervous about being with lots of new people, <strong>find a couple familiar people and ask each to invite just 1 person</strong>.
If you&rsquo;d like to do dinner in a very small group, post on one of the more active social networks and say: &ldquo;I&rsquo;m looking for a small dinner group and I&rsquo;m looking for exactly 1 or 2 or 3 (your choice) other people to do dinner with.  Any takers?&rdquo;.</p>

<p><strong>Note for 2024</strong>: unfortunately due to the fracturing of Twitter&rsquo;s previous user base into other social networks, posting on social media to ask if folks have plans doesn&rsquo;t work as well as it used to.
Sadly I don&rsquo;t have a great solution for this in 2024&hellip; I&rsquo;ll likely mostly be on Mastodon this year, but I know the activity there will be much more minimal than Twitter&rsquo;s activity used to be.</p>

<p>Sometimes people make a reservation at a restaurant and hope they can find people to join them.
I&rsquo;m not that gutsy and I usually prefer to gather people until I have a headcount and then call a nearby restaurant to ask if a reservation is needed.
During your first conference I&rsquo;m recommend <strong>walking up to a group of folks and asking &ldquo;does anyone have dinner plans?&rdquo;</strong>
Often the response will be &ldquo;we&rsquo;re trying to figure that out now, want to join us?&rdquo;</p>

<p>As far as events in the evening besides dinner go, there&rsquo;s a variety of options usually.
Some people go out drinking.
I don&rsquo;t drink, so I don&rsquo;t do this but I&rsquo;ve also heard the recommendation from drinkers that <strong>it&rsquo;s a very bad idea to drink heavily during a conference</strong>.
You&rsquo;re with people you don&rsquo;t know in a new community: don&rsquo;t increase the chance that you might alienate someone by doing something you regret.
I&rsquo;m very biased here, but I&rsquo;d drinking very moderately if you drink at all during PyCon.</p>

<p>One thing you&rsquo;ll likely see a lot of during PyCon is board games.
Folks often play board games in the hotel lobbies, in board game bars, and even in the open spaces!
PyCon&rsquo;s open spaces usually involve some evening time for after hour events and board games are frequently one of those events.
There&rsquo;s usually <strong>at least one night with a semi-official board game open spaces</strong> event, but there are often others that appear.
You could even put your own board game open space event on the board!</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t mention board games without mentioning my absolute favorite conference ice breaker: <strong>the cabo card game</strong>.
I&rsquo;ve played Cabo at <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/573027732902133760">most</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/587086868396822528">tech</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/algosuna/status/641421944005378048">conferences</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/746454264495513601">I&rsquo;ve</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/755887571264212993">been</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/treyhunner/status/897971022334382080">to</a>.
I love Cabo because it only requires a 52 card deck and using the phrase &ldquo;want to learn a 20 minute card game that I guarantee you&rsquo;ve never heard of&rdquo; seems to allow people to let their guard down and meet new people (not everyone says yes, but many people do).
If you&rsquo;d like to try playing Cabo yourself, you can read my blog post on <a href="http://treyhunner.com/2015/06/cabo-card-game/">the rules to the Cabo card game</a>.</p>

<p>The thing I love about nearly all forms of games is that your technical interests or expertise don&rsquo;t usually matter when you&rsquo;re playing a game.
You can bond with people without have any deep conversation at all.
I&rsquo;ve met people the day after playing a long game and <strong>felt like I already knew them even though I didn&rsquo;t even know their name yet</strong>.</p>

<h2>Volunteering 💝</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;re the type of person who derives comfort from understanding and being part of the inner workings of a community event, I recommend <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2024/volunteers/volunteering/">volunteering to help out while at PyCon</a>.</p>

<p>You might think it&rsquo;s premature to volunteer during your first PyCon and for some roles, it likely is.
You probably shouldn&rsquo;t volunteer to be a session chair during your first PyCon for example because that&rsquo;s a big role.
But you could absolutely be part of the <strong>swag bag stuffing</strong>, which is a way to see lots friendly of faces while being a smiling cog in a bag-stuff assembly line.</p>

<p>You could also volunteer to help <strong>hand out swag bags</strong>, act as a friendly greeter for folks coming into tutorials, or <strong>help out at the registration desk</strong>.
These might sound like scary tasks, but from my experience <strong>the folks who coordinate volunteers are happy to answer questions and prepare you for your role</strong> so that you feel comfortable doing the job you&rsquo;ve signed up for.
All three of those tasks are ways to practice being a cheerful and empathetic face, which will help other first-time attendees to feel comfortable too.</p>

<p>After volunteering, people may occasionally meet you in the hall and wonder why they&rsquo;re already familiar with your friendly face.
It&rsquo;s because you handed them their badge or checked their name off a list!
Also volunteering can give you glimpse behind the scenes of PyCon and <strong>make things feel a little less scary and official</strong>.</p>

<p>If you are planning to volunteer though, make sure you block that time off on your calendar and that you show up.
<strong>Don&rsquo;t miss your volunteering time slots and leave the staff scrambling to find someone to fill in at the last minute</strong>.</p>

<p>If volunteering to be a small part of the event inner-workings isn&rsquo;t your thing, don&rsquo;t worry.
<strong>There are lots of great ways to spend your time while at PyCon</strong>!</p>

<h2>Give a lightning talk ⚡</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;re feeling particularly bold one day, you could sign up on the <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2024/events/lightning-talks/">lightning talk board</a> to give a 5 minute lightning talk on a topic of your choosing.
This is another excuse for people to talk to you.</p>

<p>I gave my first conference lightning talk <a href="https://youtu.be/Peo-n4spSRA?t=9m59s">at DjangoCon 2015</a>, during which I compared modern JavaScript to Python.
A few people I&rsquo;d never met started a conversation with me at a bar afterward by saying &ldquo;I liked your lightning talk.&rdquo;
Lightning talks can act as an ice breaker.
If you give a talk to a giant room of people, you&rsquo;ve given everyone in that room at least a reason to talk to you.</p>

<p>If you do give a lightning talk, <strong>make sure it&rsquo;s less than 5 minutes</strong>.
You do not want to run over time in a lightning talk.
The shorter and more compact, the better.</p>

<h2>Take care of yourself 💗</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s so many people.
What do I do if I get overwhelmed?</p>

<p>While at PyCon, you&rsquo;ll want to <strong>make sure you pace yourself</strong> and that you <strong>find a way to slow down and recharge</strong> when needed.
If you&rsquo;re an introvert, your laptop&rsquo;s batteries will likely last longer than yours before needing a recharge at PyCon.
At least once a day, I&rsquo;d recommend finding a quiet place to sit, breathe deeply, think about your day, and meditate.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t expect yourself to be able to wake up, head to the conference venue, do things at every moment during the day, and then go out with folks for dinner and more conversation in the evening.
If you know your limits, respect them.
<strong>Push yourself outside of your comfort zone, but don&rsquo;t stretch your boundaries too far</strong>.
Make sure to check in with yourself and take breaks to assess whether you need mid-day a nap or a bit of quiet alone time between lunch and dinner.
<strong>You cannot be &ldquo;on&rdquo; at every moment</strong>.</p>

<h2>Tips from others 😄</h2>

<p>I can&rsquo;t write a guide on attending PyCon without referencing a couple other wonderful guides that have been written on this topic.</p>

<p>Danny Greenfeld&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.pydanny.com/beginners-guide-pycon-2014.html">Beginner&rsquo;s Guide to PyCon 2015</a> is another great guide to PyCon, with lots of tips on how to make the most of PyCon.
It&rsquo;s much more compact than my post here, so it&rsquo;s a quick and dense read.</p>

<p>Al Sweigart also talks quite a bit about his strategies for meeting new people at PyCon in his <a href="https://automatetheboringstuff.com/how-to-do-pycon.html">How to Do PyCon</a> post.
Al is also an introvert, but he&rsquo;s very good at gamifying socializing with others.</p>

<p>I also <strong>highly recommend asking questions</strong> to staff members, friendly-looking volunteers, and people with silly hats (some people use hats to indicate that they&rsquo;re approachable).
Different PyCon attendees will have different recommendations for how to make the most of PyCon without getting overwhelmed.</p>

<p>Also, if you see me in the hallway at PyCon (I have a face that looks like me and will like have a &ldquo;Trey Hunner&rdquo; name badge on), say hi and let me know you read this article! 😄</p>

<p>I hope you have a lovely PyCon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
