<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: readability | Trey Hunner]]></title>
  <link href="http://treyhunner.com/blog/categories/readability/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://treyhunner.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-02-13T17:00:24-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://treyhunner.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Trey Hunner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Craft Your Python Like Poetry]]></title>
    <link href="http://treyhunner.com/2017/07/craft-your-python-like-poetry/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-23T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://treyhunner.com/2017/07/craft-your-python-like-poetry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Line length is a big deal&hellip; programmers argue about it quite a bit.  PEP 8, the Python style guide, recommends a <a href="http://pep8.org/#maximum-line-length">79 character maximum line length</a> but concedes that a line length up to 100 characters is acceptable for teams that agree to use a specific longer line length.</p>

<p>So 79 characters is recommended&hellip; but isn&rsquo;t line length completely obsolete?  After all, programmers are no longer restricted by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punched_card">punch cards</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teletype_Corporation">teletypes</a>, and 80 column <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_terminal">terminals</a>.  The laptop screen I&rsquo;m typing this on can fit about 200 characters per line.</p>

<h2>Line length is not obsolete</h2>

<p>Line length is not a technical limitation: it&rsquo;s a human-imposed limitation.  Many programmers prefer short lines because <strong>long lines are hard to read</strong>.  This is true in typography and it&rsquo;s true in programming as well.</p>

<p>Short lines are easier to read.</p>

<p>In the typography world, a line length of 55 characters per line is recommended for electronic text (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Line_length">line length on Wikipedia</a>).  That doesn&rsquo;t mean we should use a 55 character limit though; typography and programming are different.</p>

<h2>Python isn&rsquo;t prose</h2>

<p>Python code isn&rsquo;t structured like prose.  English prose is structured in flowing sentences: each line wraps into the next line.  In Python, <strong>statements</strong> are somewhat like <strong>sentences</strong>, meaning each sentence begins at the <em>start</em> of each line.</p>

<p>Python code is more like poetry than prose.  Poets and Python programmers don&rsquo;t wrap lines once they hit an arbitrary length; they wrap lines when they make sense for readability and beauty.</p>

<pre><code>I stand amid the roar Of a surf-tormented shore, And I hold within my hand
Grains of the golden sand— How few! yet how they creep Through my fingers to
the deep, While I weep—while I weep! O God! can I not grasp Them with a
tighter clasp? O God! can I not save One from the pitiless wave? Is all that we
see or seem But a dream within a dream?
</code></pre>

<p>Don&rsquo;t wrap lines arbitrarily. Craft each line with care to help readers <strong>experience your code exactly the way you intended</strong>.</p>

<pre><code>I stand amid the roar
Of a surf-tormented shore,
And I hold within my hand
Grains of the golden sand—
How few! yet how they creep
Through my fingers to the deep,
While I weep—while I weep!
O God! can I not grasp
Them with a tighter clasp?
O God! can I not save
One from the pitiless wave?
Is all that we see or seem
But a dream within a dream?
</code></pre>

<h2>Examples</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not possible to make a single rule for when and how to wrap lines of code.  <a href="http://pep8.org/#indentation">PEP8 discusses line wrapping briefly</a>, but it only discusses one case of line wrapping and three different acceptable styles are provided, leaving the reader to choose which is best.</p>

<p>Line wrapping is best discussed through examples.  Let&rsquo;s look at a few examples of long lines and few variations for line wrapping for each.</p>

<h3>Example: Wrapping a Comprehension</h3>

<p>This line of code is over 79 characters long:</p>

<pre><code class="python">employee_hours = [schedule.earliest_hour for employee in self.public_employees for schedule in employee.schedules]
</code></pre>

<p>Here we&rsquo;ve wrapped that line of code so that it&rsquo;s two shorter lines of code:</p>

<pre><code class="python">employee_hours = [schedule.earliest_hour for employee in
                  self.public_employees for schedule in employee.schedules]
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;re able to insert that line break in this line because we have an <strong>unclosed square bracket</strong>.  This is called an <strong>implicit line continuation</strong>.  Python knows we&rsquo;re continuing a line of code whenever there&rsquo;s a line break inside unclosed square brackets, curly braces, or parentheses.</p>

<p>This code still isn&rsquo;t very easy to read because the line break was inserted arbitrarily.  We simply wrapped this line just before a specific line length.  We were thinking about line length here, but we completely neglected to think about readability.</p>

<p>This code is the same as above, but we&rsquo;ve inserted line breaks in very particular places:</p>

<pre><code class="python">employee_hours = [schedule.earliest_hour
                  for employee in self.public_employees
                  for schedule in employee.schedules]
</code></pre>

<p>We have two lines breaks here and we&rsquo;ve purposely inserted them before our <code>for</code> clauses in this list comprehension.</p>

<p>Statements have logical components that make up a whole, the same way sentences have clauses that make up the whole.  We&rsquo;ve chosen to break up this list comprehension by inserting line breaks <strong>between these logical components</strong>.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s another way to break up this statement:</p>

<pre><code class="python">employee_hours = [
    schedule.earliest_hour
    for employee in self.public_employees
    for schedule in employee.schedules
]
</code></pre>

<p>Which of these methods you prefer is up to you.  It&rsquo;s important to make sure you break up the logical components though.  And whichever method you choose, <strong>be consistent</strong>!</p>

<h3>Example: Function Calls</h3>

<p>This is a Django model field with a whole bunch of arguments being passed to it:</p>

<pre><code class="python">default_appointment = models.ForeignKey(othermodel='AppointmentType',
                                        null=True, on_delete=models.SET_NULL,
                                        related_name='+')
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;re already using an implicit line continuation to wrap these lines of code, but again we&rsquo;re wrapping this code at an arbitrary line length.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the same Django model field with one argument specific per line:</p>

<pre><code class="python">default_appointment = models.ForeignKey(othermodel='AppointmentType',
                                        null=True,
                                        on_delete=models.SET_NULL,
                                        related_name='+')
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;re breaking up the component parts (the arguments) of this statement onto separate lines.</p>

<p>We could also wrap this line by indenting each argument instead of aligning them:</p>

<pre><code class="python">default_appointment = models.ForeignKey(
    othermodel='AppointmentType',
    null=True,
    on_delete=models.SET_NULL,
    related_name='+'
)
</code></pre>

<p>Notice we&rsquo;re also leaving that closing parenthesis on its own line.  We could additionally add a trailing comma if we wanted:</p>

<pre><code class="python">default_appointment = models.ForeignKey(
    othermodel='AppointmentType',
    null=True,
    on_delete=models.SET_NULL,
    related_name='+',
)
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Which of these is the best way to wrap this line?</strong></p>

<p>Personally for this line I prefer that last approach: each argument on its own line, the closing parenthesis on its own line, and a comma after each argument.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s important to decide what you prefer, reflect on why you prefer it, and always maintain consistency within each project/file you create.  And keep in mind that consistence of your personal style is less important than <strong>consistency within a single project</strong>.</p>

<h3>Example: Chained Function Calls</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a long line of chained Django queryset methods:</p>

<pre><code class="python">    books = Book.objects.filter(author__in=favorite_authors).select_related('author', 'publisher').order_by('title')
</code></pre>

<p>Notice that there aren&rsquo;t parenthesis around this whole statement, so the only place we can currently wrap our lines is inside those parenthesis.  We could do something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="python">    books = Book.objects.filter(
        author__in=favorite_authors
    ).select_related(
        'author', 'publisher'
    ).order_by('title')
</code></pre>

<p>But that looks kind of weird and it doesn&rsquo;t really improve readability.</p>

<p>We could add backslashes at the end of each line to allow us to wrap at arbitrary places:</p>

<pre><code class="python">    books = Book.objects\
        .filter(author__in=favorite_authors)\
        .select_related('author', 'publisher')\
        .order_by('title')
</code></pre>

<p>This works, but <a href="http://pep8.org/#maximum-line-length">PEP8 recommends against this</a>.</p>

<p>We could wrap the whole statement in parenthesis, allowing us to use implicit line continuation wherever we&rsquo;d like:</p>

<pre><code class="python">    books = (Book.objects
        .filter(author__in=favorite_authors)
        .select_related('author', 'publisher')
        .order_by('title'))
</code></pre>

<p>It&rsquo;s not uncommon to see extra parenthesis added in Python code to allow implicit line continuations.</p>

<p>That indentation style is a little odd though.  We could align our code with the parenthesis instead:</p>

<pre><code class="python">    books = (Book.objects
             .filter(author__in=favorite_authors)
             .select_related('author', 'publisher')
             .order_by('title'))
</code></pre>

<p>Although I&rsquo;d probably prefer to align the dots in this case:</p>

<pre><code class="python">    books = (Book.objects
                 .filter(author__in=favorite_authors)
                 .select_related('author', 'publisher')
                 .order_by('title'))
</code></pre>

<p>A fully indentation-based style works too (we&rsquo;ve also moved <code>objects</code> to its own line here):</p>

<pre><code class="python">    books = (
        Book
        .objects
        .filter(author__in=favorite_authors)
        .select_related('author', 'publisher')
        .order_by('title')
    )
</code></pre>

<p>There are yet more ways to resolve this problem.  For example we could try to use intermediary variables to avoid line wrapping entirely.</p>

<p>Chained methods pose a different problem for line wrapping than single method calls and require a different solution.  Focus on readability when picking a preferred solution and be consistent with the solution you pick.  <strong>Consistency lies at the heart of readability</strong>.</p>

<h3>Example: Dictionary Literals</h3>

<p>I often define long dictionaries and lists defined in Python code.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a dictionary definition that has been over multiple lines, with line breaks inserted as a maximum line length is approached:</p>

<pre><code class="python">MONTHS = {'January': 1, 'February': 2, 'March': 3, 'April': 4, 'May': 5,
          'June': 6, 'July': 7, 'August': 8, 'September': 9, 'October': 10,
          'November': 11, 'December': 12}
</code></pre>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the same dictionary with each key-value pair on its own line, aligned with the first key-value pair:</p>

<pre><code class="python">MONTHS = {'January': 1,
          'February': 2,
          'March': 3,
          'April': 4,
          'May': 5,
          'June': 6,
          'July': 7,
          'August': 8,
          'September': 9,
          'October': 10,
          'November': 11,
          'December': 12}
</code></pre>

<p>And the same dictionary again, with each key-value pair indented instead of aligned (with a trailing comma on the last line as well):</p>

<pre><code class="python">MONTHS = {
    'January': 1,
    'February': 2,
    'March': 3,
    'April': 4,
    'May': 5,
    'June': 6,
    'July': 7,
    'August': 8,
    'September': 9,
    'October': 10,
    'November': 11,
    'December': 12,
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is the strategy I prefer for wrapping long dictionaries and lists.  I very often wrap short dictionaries and lists this way as well, for the sake of readability.</p>

<h2>Python is Poetry</h2>

<p>The moment of <strong>peak readability</strong> is <strong>the moment just after you write a line of code</strong>.  Your code will be far less readable to you one day, one week, and one month after you&rsquo;ve written it.</p>

<p>When crafting Python code, use spaces and line breaks to split up the logical components of each statement.  Don&rsquo;t write a statement on a single line unless it&rsquo;s already <em>very</em> clear.  If you break each line over multiple lines for clarity, lines length shouldn&rsquo;t be a major concern because your lines of code will mostly be far shorter than 79 characters already.</p>

<p>Make sure to craft your code carefully as you write it because your future self will have a much more difficult time cleaning it up than you will <strong>right now</strong>.  So take that line of code you just wrote and carefully add line breaks to it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
